Welcome back to Programming for a Networked World.
Today we're going to be continuing our exploration of the chart RPC.
But I'm going to let you in on a little secret.
Last time we had nicely formatted data,
a list of lists that we passed into the chart EPC, RPC,
and then got back a good graphic.
But your data doesn't always come nicely packaged as a list of lists.
So what do you do then?
We're going to learn how to apply our knowledge of how to work with lists
so that we can format our data in a way that makes it easy to chart.
Let's get started.
Okay, so here's our plan.
We're going to look at the difference between linear growth and exponential growth.
And we're going to do that by combining two lists.
A list of numbers, just say 1 to 15,
and then those numbers either multiplied by 2 or squared.
But to do this, we need to combine two lists.
The first list of our initial numbers,
and then the list of those numbers with the mathematical function applied to them.
Okay, so how do we do that?
Well, to get started, we can just make a list of lists.
So that's easy enough.
We'll go down to our lists here and let's take a look.
There's numbers 1 to 10.
If we click on that, we get 1 to 10.
Let's just change it 1 to 15.
There we go.
And now how do we get the list of numbers with the function applied?
Well, that's also fairly easy to do here
because we can take one of these blocks here that's like square root,
and we can drop down and we can find, for example, 2 times.
Here we go.
And if we pass that in,
you see that it automatically applies that function to every item in the list.
So that's great.
We have now our list of numbers 1 to 15,
and then we have the squares from 1 to 15,
and we can do the same thing, of course,
if we come over here and we get the multiply by 2.
Let's do that.
So we'll say 2 times, and then we're going to make a copy of the numbers.
We'll duplicate that.
And again, it produces a nice list for us of those numbers multiplied by 2.
The trouble comes in when we want to actually combine these lists
because, as you know, the chart RPC requires us to pass in a list of lists.
And here we have two single lists side by side.
So we need to combine them.
And this operation in programming speech is called zipping the lists.
That is taking one list and another
and making a list out of a list or a matrix out of them.
So how do we go about doing that?
Well, let's develop a block that will help us.
We're going to call this block join.
All right, so let's just create a new block here.
And we're going to call it join.
And it's going to be a reporter.
So we're just going to say join, let's say, list 1 and list 2.
So now, and maybe we'll call it join list just to be clear that it's not joining strings.
And we're going to turn that to reporter,
and we're going to put it into the operations category here.
And now we're going to take that and make it an input.
And the input type is going to be a list.
And that's good.
I'm going to say okay.
Here we go.
And here, do the same thing.
I'm going to make that a list.
Say okay to that.
Okay, so there's the block that we'll be working with.
And now, how do we start putting these together?
Well, first let's create a variable called matrix.
So let's see, under variables here, we'll make it a script variable
because we just want to contain it within the block.
Call it matrix.
There we go.
And now we're going to iterate through the length of this list.
And then we're going to, for each item in one list,
we'll add the second item, and then we'll send back a combined list.
Now the trick is you should make sure that the lists going in here are the same length
because if they aren't, you might have unexpected results.
We're going to assume for the sake of this demonstration that they are.
Okay, so we'll just take a loop here.
We'll say like a for loop.
And here we go.
And we'll say from 1 until the length of list 1.
And now what do we do?
Well, we want to combine those lists.
So we're going to make a new list,
and we're going to use this add function here.
Find it down towards the bottom.
There we go.
And what we're going to add is a list
because this is a list of lists,
so we're going to add a list right here
like that with two slots.
And we're going to take item 1 of the first list
and item 1 of the second list.
But of course, we don't want it to be item 1 each time.
That would make the list of only the first items.
We want it to be item i and item i of the first list
and of the second list.
And then we're going to assign those to matrix.
Now, the only other thing that we need to remember is
we need to make sure that matrix is given the type of a list
so that when we first assign lists to it,
the compiler doesn't complain,
or the interpreter, I should say, doesn't complain.
Okay, so let's do that.
And here we're going to set under variables matrix
to an empty list.
That'll help us get started.
All right.
So this operation, again, is called zipping a list,
and let's see if it works as we expect.
So I'll say done, and we'll go to custom blocks here.
I'm going to grab this join list,
and now let's get our numbers from 1 to 10.
So we'll duplicate this.
And again, it's 1 to 15, I should say.
That's fine.
So we're going to pass that in as the first list,
and then let's do this one,
which are the squares of those numbers,
as the second list.
There we go.
And let's try it out.
And okay, we're getting an error.
So let's take a look.
Set matrix to list for i equals 1 to length of list.
Oh, this needs to be the length of list 1.
All right, let's do that.
Let's go under lists here
and get the length of because there we go.
Not just the list, but the length of the list.
And now we didn't get a report.
Let's go check out what's going on here.
Ah, yes.
It would be helpful to add a report to the list at the end.
So let's do that.
All the simple things we need to remember
when we're making blocks.
All right, so let's get our report here,
which should be...
There we go.
Report.
Okay.
And now we're going to report the matrix.
And that is, in fact, what our chart service needs.
So if we go back out to our chart service,
we can go here to network.
Let's bring over our chart.
Drop down.
And we're going to just do the draw.
And remember, we discovered we don't need default options
if we're just going to keep the options in place.
And we can take this here as our lines.
And we'll have to say goodbye to eta,
but because we want to plot this on the screen,
we're going to put that switch to costume there.
There we go.
And let's try it out.
So that is a chart of exponential growth.
And if we want to do a similar chart of linear growth,
it would just be a question of changing
this particular function right here.
We'll put that two times in here.
And let's look at the difference between exponential
and linear growth.
And there you go.
So that's a linear function as opposed to an exponential one.
Okay.
So the main thing is those zipping operations
are things that you're going to run into all the time
if you need to chart, because you always need something
for the x-axis and another list for the y-axis.
Now, I'll let you in on yet another secret.
If you don't want to write those zipping functions yourself,
Brian has already written one for us.
And you can find this under here.
If you go to Libraries and you click on Libraries,
and then this is a tab that we haven't used before.
It's called Community.
And community libraries are libraries that are provided
by members of the NetSplocks community,
and you can access them here.
And so if you look and we type in zip,
you can see that there is a zip library.
And if you drop down, you can see that it has
a function called zip.
So let's try this out.
We're going to substitute the zip function that we've written,
which is join list here, and let's use Brian's.
So in this case, you see that it takes a single list,
but we need to expand it to contain two.
We're going to drop our numbers in here.
There's the first slot.
And then we want to drop this function into the second slot,
and let's see if it produces a list.
There it does.
That's our linear list.
Let's do the exponential one.
There we go.
We'll click on that, and you can see that it works
in exactly the same way.
Now, if you look under the covers,
the operations are different.
I'll leave that to you to explore how Brian
has implemented this function.
But let's just drop it back for completeness sake
into our charting operation and see if it works.
It needs to go into the line slot, not into the options.
Let's switch to costume, and there we have it.
Okay, so in this video, you learned what zipping a list is.
It's taking a list of numbers and another list of numbers
and then combining them into a matrix.
And you learned that you need to do that
when you want to chart operations in which you need
to have an x-axis and a y-axis.
And you also learned a little bit about how you can use
community-contributed libraries like Brian's
if you don't want to write those kind of functions yourself.
Although, that's the fun of programming, of course.
All right, that's it for today.
I look forward to seeing you in our next video.