Hi, everyone. Welcome back to Programming for a Networked World.
Today, we're going to be talking about
a fundamental control structure called loops.
Loops help you to automate repetitive tasks,
so that you don't have to have blocks that
just repeat themselves over and over again.
You can put them inside a loop and have the loop do the work for you.
But it's also important to know how to
stop a loop when you want to move on to another task.
So, ready to loop-de-loop the way through nets blocks?
Let's get started.
Okay. So today,
we're going to be talking about four types of loops,
and let's just find where the loops are.
So if we go over here to control structures,
you'll see, there we go, control structures.
You'll see that we've got down here four types of loops,
and we're going to spring them out.
So forever, then there's the repeat,
repeat until, and this last one,
which has this strange looking variable in it.
Okay. So let's just start at the top and see how a forever loop works.
Now, a forever loop, as the name implies,
just keeps going forever.
So let's imagine that we wanted Ada to count up as high as she possibly could,
just count until the end of the world, let's say.
How would we do that?
Well, we would start with a variable.
So let's create a variable over here,
and we're going to make this variable count.
Okay. Then we'll set count at the beginning here,
right like that, and we'll set count to one.
I'm not going to have count up here on the stage because we'll have Ada actually say it.
Now, we want to change the count by one as we go through the loop.
There we go. We need to have Ada say the count.
So that should actually be under looks.
There we go. Let's say this here.
To do that, I'm going to just make a little more space for myself.
To do that, we need to bring that variable count here into the say block,
and we're going to reduce the time so it's a little bit faster.
We'll put a nice hat block on the top to start it all off.
Okay. So this will just have Ada counting forever,
at least until the end of the program.
Ready? So there you go.
Ada's counting, and you can see that it's still executing,
and it'll just repeat what's inside of this forever block until we stop it.
So I'm going to click on again to stop it.
Okay. But sometimes you don't want to do something forever.
You want to do something like a defined number of times.
So here, for example,
we have repeat 10,
and this could be repeat any number of times,
but we'll just stay with 10.
We can actually just take most of what we've written over here and duplicate it.
So I'm going to pull this part out.
I'm going to click on it,
and then I'm going to say duplicate,
and drop that back in,
and drop it over here,
and let's do the same thing with this part right here.
So I'm going to, there we go.
Let's duplicate this and bring it over here,
put it back together like that.
Okay. Then we want a nice hat block here too.
All right. So we want to set this count though to 0.
This is actually supposed to be set to 0.
So let's do that.
Okay. Or 1, let's say.
I've got to start it again.
Okay. So now let's try this other one.
Now, what you see here is that this will repeat 10 times.
So it really doesn't matter what the count variable is.
It will just repeat it 10 times.
So for this one, in order to not confuse it with the other one,
we won't have space for the hat block.
Let's use just 1.
Okay. So when I press 1 and I click on this,
you see that it counts up to 10 and then it stops.
Now, we could actually have a count from any number we wanted.
It doesn't have to be 10. It could start counting from 20,
for example, and the same block.
Oops. Let's do that right there.
The same block will count up just another 10 times.
So the point is it will repeat itself 10 times and then stop.
Now, there may be times when you want to stop the loop based
on a particular condition that you encounter within the loop.
It's a very common scenario, for example,
to have a loop until you reach some kind of threshold.
So for example, here,
we might say let's count up,
but when you get to 15, then stop.
But it may not be 15 repetitions.
It may just be until you reach 15.
So let's set that up.
So the way that we'll do that,
we'll duplicate this part here like this and drop this back in.
Now, we need to set that condition.
So to do that, we're going to go over to our Boolean operators here.
Let's just say if it's greater than or equal to,
here we go, like this.
Greater than 15 or equal to 15,
then that will be what we use to decide when to stop this loop.
So what we need here then is that variable again.
We're going to throw a count in the front here,
count here, and drop that into our Boolean condition.
Let's put a hat block on this one,
but just get this out of the way.
We're going to have a different key to start this one.
We'll say this one will be 2.
So when I press 2,
this is going to start counting.
We should actually make sure that we reset count.
So let's do that and let's set it to 1.
Now, this will count up until 15.
So we can just try that out.
Let's see how it works.
Oops, I had it set for 12.
So you can see it reached actually 15 and stopped.
So if we do it for 1 now,
let's try that.
There we go. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7,
it counts pretty fast.
But you can see that as we approach 15, it stopped.
Now, the thing is it actually didn't say 15.
Did you notice that? Let's just try this again at,
let's say, 13, 13, 14, and then it stops.
The reason is, it's checking that condition
before it goes into the loop.
So if you actually want it to reach 15 and then stop,
you need to set this for 1 higher.
So for example, if it's greater than 15 or equal to 16.
So let's try that now.
13, 14, 15, and then it stops.
Okay. So you can see that this particular loop
checks its condition before it enters the loop,
and if the condition is met,
then it moves on and skips the loop,
goes to the next set of blocks that are below the loop.
There are other control structures
that check the condition at the end of the loop.
So to get to those,
you'd have to go over here,
click on this white page,
and then go to libraries and type in iteration,
and you get iteration composition.
You'll see that it brings up,
if I can open this up a little bit more,
several other types of iterators or loops,
and you can see that one of them is
going to be repeat until at the bottom.
So this one will actually always execute
and then check the condition at the bottom.
So depending on what type of loop you're setting up,
that is an option.
If you do want to use this option,
then you need to open this library,
and you can import it here,
and you'll see those blocks now under the custom tab.
So we could pull in this repeat until right here,
and we can set up that loop,
but now check the condition at the exit of the loop.
All right, the last loop that I want to talk
about is this for loop here.
This is a bit of a different loop,
and it really just incorporates a shortcut.
You know we've been creating
this count variable for each one of these loops,
but the for loop allows you to create a loop without
making a specific variable in advance.
It actually just has a variable built in.
Typically that variable is called I,
but if you wanted to, you could change it to count
just by clicking on it and renaming it.
It doesn't have any special meaning.
And here you can see count from one to 10,
and it's going to loop,
and it's going to count each time it goes through.
So what that allows you to do is to save this extra step
of setting the counter and then incrementing the counter
as you go through the loop.
So all we need to do to use this block
is to copy this piece here.
Let me do that.
I'm going to duplicate this, bring it down here.
Let's put this one back together where it should be.
Okay, and let's put a hat block on this one too,
if I can get enough space here in the scripting area.
All right, and I'm going to put a hat block
on this for loop, and let's call this one three.
So when I press three, then I'll go through that loop,
and you can see that this counter will automatically
take care of where it is in the loop.
And let's just see how that works.
One, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight, nine,
and it goes to 10, and then it stops.
So all these loops are available to you,
and as you saw, there are even more loops
behind the scenes in libraries and nets blocks
that you can use.
And the purpose of all of the loops
is to make your programs more efficient.
Whether you're going to be counting up to a certain number
or performing an operation a certain number of times,
the loops help you to set conditions about when to stop,
when to move on to something else.
It could just be a certain number of repetitions.
It could be when you meet a particular threshold,
and it helps to organize your program
and stop you from having to repeat blocks
over and over again in series.
All right, so that's everything we had to say today
about looping, and I look forward to seeing you
in my next video.