Hi, everyone.
Welcome back to Programming for a Networked World.
Today, we're going to continue our exploration of networking
within Netsblocks.
But in our previous examples, we've
used the room with various roles.
This time, we're not going to do that,
because when you're building certain types of applications,
and we'll be building a client server application,
you don't always know the number of users you're going to have.
And you don't want to, as you expand or contract,
have to create new roles or delete roles
as users come and go.
So in this particular application,
we're going to be messaging each other back and forth
with another way of passing information between Netsblocks
programs called a public role ID.
So to begin with, we're just going
to start with that simple exchange of messages
between computers.
And so we'll go over to Brian's side.
And he's going to set up the environment in which we
can receive the message.
And then I'll pass the message to him.
All right, so if we remember back to earlier projects,
like our distributed Hello World,
we have this network category where we have all our message
passing blocks.
So we can use this when I receive message handler
to handle messages that we received over the network.
So if we click on this dropdown, we
can select the built-in message type for now.
You might want to change this later,
but it's a decent starting spot.
And then when we receive the message, let's keep it simple
and just save the message for two seconds.
So we can use this save block and then
drag the contents of the message, which this message
type only has a single field, MSG.
And we can just save this for two seconds.
And then now we just need somebody
to send us a message that we can then display.
So with that, I'll hand it over to Cliff.
OK, so when I want to send a message to Brian,
let me bring this over here.
Now, the problem is I can send a message.
That's fine, and I can say, hello, Brian.
But the problem is we're not sharing a project.
So it's not going to be helpful to say to others in the room
or everyone in a room, because we're actually not in a room
together at this point.
We're just in completely separate Nets Blocks projects.
So how do I actually get the message to you, Brian?
That is a good question.
So in Nets Blocks and under this network category,
we have services and RPCs that we've seen before.
And there's one service in particular
that can be useful here.
It's this public roles service.
This lets us get a public role ID.
So in the past, when we were communicating within a room,
we had multiple roles, and we were just
using the role ID or role name to communicate
with one another.
Now, even if different projects had roles with the same name,
it was no problem to resolve this role name,
because we knew that it was within the room.
But as Cliff mentioned earlier, we're not using a room here.
So we need some sort of absolute or unique address
for the specific project or role that we are
wanting to send a message to.
So if we call this get public role ID,
this will return a public role ID or this kind of unique role
or this unique address for your specific role and project
that we can see here.
So when we click on it, we see this little dialog bubble
pop up that says my role at chat server at Brian.
So it looks a little bit like an email address.
But essentially, if we break it down,
it is your role name at your project name
at your username, which, of course, then is unique.
So to make this a little bit easier for anyone
who might want to connect to this server,
I'll just make a little server address variable, which
I can set when the project starts.
And let's say when the green flag is clicked,
this value will be set.
And now we can see I have this server address little watcher
showing up on the stage, which has the public role
ID or fully qualified kind of unique address
for this specific program.
So the thing is that public role ID is just like an email.
And I remember in the beginning of email back in the 90s
when people were first starting to use email,
the trick was how do you discover someone's email
address?
Because if you don't have their email address,
you can't email them.
And so this is the same problem here.
I actually have to learn that address from Brian.
He has to be able to give it to me in some way.
Otherwise, I can't communicate with him.
So in this case, since he's right next to me,
I'll ask him.
You could have him email your address.
There are other ways to share it.
But you do need to know what his public role
ID is going to be in order to start
the chain of communication.
So I'm going to do the same thing.
I'm going to go over here.
And I'm going to create a variable.
Let's just, I always like to use the script variables.
Let's just do that.
And I'm going to call this one, let's say, well, you know what?
I think Brian is probably thinking,
don't do it this time.
Let's just make a public variable.
Because I may need to use it in various places.
So we're going to call this, let's call it the chat server
ID.
So that's where the chat server is going to be.
And we're going to set that chat server here
to what Brian's public role is.
Now, just tell me, and I'll type it in.
Sure.
So it's my role at chat server.
And there's a space between chat and server.
And I capitalized the C and the S.
It's all very important.
I get it exactly right.
Chat server.
And then at Brian.
Brian, lowercase.
Yep.
OK.
So if I click on that, let's actually just send a message
here.
So I'm going to send that.
And instead of sending it to a room,
I'm going to drop this in here.
And now let's send the message, hello, Brian.
All right, so we didn't see a pop-up on my screen.
And this likely means that there's a typo.
Because, of course, these are sensitive,
just like email addresses, if there's
a typo or things like that.
OK, so let's go over it one more time, then.
So I think we need to change the M to be lowercase.
OK.
Because it is case-sensitive.
Yeah, so it's a lowercase M-Y, capital R-O-L-E.
OK, let's try it again.
All right.
Ah, there it goes.
OK.
There we are.
Awesome.
So now at this point, we've been able to basically recreate
the distributed Hello World project,
but not using the room concept.
Now, again, the room concept, although it's normally
a nice fit, because it makes it a lot easier
to discover addresses.
You don't have to enter or type these addresses in by hand.
You can see who's occupying the role, et cetera.
They're not the best fit for this project,
because we want to have chat clients come and go
as they please.
So we want the size of the chat room to be dynamic.
So at this point, we've been able to, again, recreate this.
But there's one big shortcoming.
So right now, when Cliff sends a message to, unfortunately,
he's the only person in the room.
But he can just lean over and look at my screen,
I guess, to see what everyone's been saying.
But of course, this isn't really ideal,
because you don't want to always have
to be in the same room as the server program.
So we really need the server to not just display the message,
but actually to send it to the people in the conversation
or in the chat room.
So if we're going to do something like that,
when we receive this message, instead
of saying it for two seconds, we would just
want to send it to, in this case, just Cliff.
But we really want to send it to all the people in the room.
So basically, we're forwarding the same message back.
But then the problem is, how does the server
know who's all involved in the room?
So we might want to add a login or register
or some sort of step like that.
I'm going to call it a registration step.
And I'm going to make a new message type for this.
So this would be a step where the person who
wants to join the server sends them a register
message to the server that just has one field,
and that's their address.
And then we will record this as someone
who cares about the conversation or someone who's in the chat room
and to whom we'll send any messages that we receive
from some of the current occupants.
So we can add a new message handler now
for the register message type, which, again,
has a single field called address.
And then we can make a new variable
to say that we have a number of connected clients.
And we just add the current address to the clients.
Now, there are a couple of little things
we might want to keep in mind.
One is that right now, if we look at our stage,
we can see clients is number 0 when we really probably
want it to be a list.
So we should initialize this variable to an empty list
when the program starts.
And we probably don't want to have duplicate entries
in our list of clients.
So we really only want to add them to the list
or add the client to the list if they're not already
in the list.
So just a couple of little edge cases, I guess, to consider.
So if it's not the case that clients already
contains the list or the address name in its list,
then we'll add it.
All right, so now we're able to actually build up
this list of clients.
And then when we receive this message,
we can just send it to our list of clients.
OK, so on my end, then I need to register with the chat server
now.
We've got an additional level of formality
that we didn't have before.
And so what I need to do first is
to recreate that same message type down here.
So let's go to make a message type.
And again, I need to know what that message type is.
And I believe it's register.
So we're going to do that.
And then the field here is going to be, I think it's,
did you call it?
ADDRESS, all lowercase.
OK, address, because that's going to be my public role ID.
OK, and so when we bring that over,
let's just kind of look at sending that message.
So we can drop this down here.
And we'll do a register.
And it should say address.
And then two, we know where it needs to go to.
It needs to go to the chat server.
So let's go over there to get that variable.
Here we go, chat server ID.
And again, to get my address, then I'm
going to go back out to network here.
And I'm going to go to the call block,
as Brian did the same way before.
And I can get my own by looking for public role ID.
There we go.
And dropping it down to get.
And then you can see that that is my particular role ID.
And so I want to send that address to register.
So you probably want to put this into your initial starting
block, so when clicked.
And I guess I probably should have used a different block
to do this.
Could have used this one here.
But let's just have it for now.
Maybe we can just report this.
There we go.
Oh, and I've got, and wait, I really
picked the wrong block here.
So we'll just pull these pieces out, actually.
I think that'll be easier.
So we're going to send a message using this one.
And there we go.
Let's drop this down to register.
There's the address.
And make some space here so we can see it.
Sorry, Ada.
There we go.
And to the chat server.
So that should be good.
Don't need this.
And so now when I first start off,
this will register me with the chat server.
So let's see if that works.
Click.
All right, so on my side, we see an error, expecting a list
but getting a number.
So.
We've run into that one before.
Yeah, so that usually means that somewhere where it, well,
as it says it was expecting a list,
it was not getting a list.
It was getting a number instead.
So if we look at these blocks, because there
aren't too many here, we see that we're
checking to see if clients contains the address.
Well, the address should be the public role ID
that Cliff sent.
And clients, if we look at the value, is zero.
So it looks like, although we wrote the code
to initialize this client's variable to an empty list,
we never ran it.
So let's click the green flag.
And then I'm going to click on this message handler.
So it's, actually, I think it should be fine.
Now, if Cliff runs it again.
One second.
So, one moment.
I seem to see, usually just clicking on those queers,
it's a little bit surprised to see that it's not.
So I'm going to just use a different message handler
quick.
All right, so now Cliff sends this again,
this register message.
Now we can see that clients actually
has his public role ID.
So we see the role name at his project name at his username.
All right, so now let's see what happens
if Cliff sends a message.
All right, so we removed the save block from ours
since we were just relaying the message back.
So now it's not showing up here.
We could add that if we want to maybe debug.
We probably want to get rid of the two seconds portion
here so that we don't slow down the messages
that we can receive.
And now if Cliff sends it again, we
can double check that we are getting the message, in fact.
But we don't yet see it on Cliff's screen
because he doesn't have any message
handler for these messages that have been, again,
kind of passed on back to the clients.
Right, so the message that I'm sending
is still a very simple message type.
Just message and then, hello, Brian.
So we want to make this a little bit more complex.
We want to be able to not only register with the chat server,
but we also want, when we send a message,
to indicate that we were the ones that sent the message.
And you could do this for different reasons.
One is you might not want to always echo back your messages
but just see other people's messages.
In this particular case, we're going
to echo back my message because it's just Brian and me.
But the point is, when you send a message
and you've got a big chat server,
you need to know who sent that message
and then the content of the message.
So for that reason, let's change our message type
from this simple message type.
We're going to create a new message type.
And then you can see here that I can expand the fields.
So we're going to make two fields.
And I'm going to call this, we can call this chat.
I guess we can call it chat.
And then the first field will be ID.
And the second field will be message.
How about that?
Now, the key is, as long as Brian
enters the same message type on his end,
we'll be able to communicate very smoothly.
OK.
So let's bring this new message type over.
Here we go.
And you know what?
This code, by the way, for setting the ID
should go up here when green flag is clicked.
And just to make this a little bit nicer,
let's add some code around this.
So when we start, let's have a sensing here and say,
ask your name, and say, what is your message, and wait.
And then we're going to put the answer here
in our new message type, which is chat.
And the answer will go into the message.
So that's good.
And then we can also capture our public role ID somewhere else.
So we've got that right here.
We probably should create a variable for that.
So let's just do that, too.
So we're going to make a variable
and call it client ID.
And then we're going to drop client ID over here.
And then I'm going to put my ID for the role right there.
OK.
So that sets up stuff in the beginning.
And then we'll register this.
We still need the address, which is we
need my address, which is going to be client ID to register
at the server ID.
OK.
Then here, probably we want something to start this off.
So we say, maybe under control, I guess.
When space key is pressed, that will kick off
sending a message.
Just to clean the screen up.
Well, for now, we leave it like that.
OK.
So when we press the space key, then we'll say,
what is your message?
Then we'll enter the message.
And we're going to send over the client ID here
with the answer to our message.
And we're going to be sending that to the chat server.
So there we go.
That should be enough to send this now,
saying who we are, what our message is,
to the right place.
So let's just try it.
We're going to instantiate everything
so we get the IDs correctly.
And I'm going to stop showing them because they're
a little annoying.
And then let's just press space.
And Ada says, what is your message?
And I'll say, hello, Brian.
Did you get this message?
And let me try to send it.
All right, so now we received the message.
Now, I did make a couple little updates,
updating this chat message handler
to have the ID and message fields,
just like Cliff had created, and to relay that chat message
back.
Right now, we're just saying the contents of the message.
And we might want to include the ID.
So let's try sending that message one more time, Cliff.
Sure.
So I have to actually type it again.
I'll say, hello times 2.
Perfect.
All right, so now we see this message
is displayed, again, in this debug display view,
not really intended to be where all of the chat
clients read the message.
But we do see the ID of the sender and the message.
Now, we might want to use the ID here.
We might want to change that to the username,
using the username block under the sensing category.
It's a little bit up to the user.
But it might be nice to have a more human-readable format
for the address.
So we could actually change this chat message type, right?
Let's go down and let's go to Network.
And we could click on the type.
Let's see, did I get the?
I guess I'd have to just make a new type.
You could do that.
Or you could just actually use the, under the Sensing tab,
pass the username block as your ID.
Think of it like your user ID, as opposed to your address.
Let's do that.
I was thinking we could send all three pieces of information.
But yeah, that would work, too.
So pick your poison.
But for now, let's just do the username, which is my?
All the way at the bottom.
All the way at the bottom, OK.
I've not used this much before.
There we go, username.
OK, and so we would take that client ID out,
put the username in.
And let's see if we can send it below once more.
There we go.
Cool, now we can see that Cliff's username is sent
as the ID with the message.
Now, as Cliff mentioned, there are a lot of different ways
you can design these systems, usually
with a lot of their own affordances and stuff as well.
For example, you could have the register message register
the username, and then just use the client's address
to resolve to the username.
So it can't be spoofed quite as easily and things like that.
But for now, I think we'll keep it simple
and just stick with the design that we have currently.
So now at this point, we've been able to register
different clients, build up this list of these clients,
and send messages to the server.
And the server then relays them back.
But we aren't yet showing these messages on our chat client.
So I think next, Cliff, if you want
to take us through how we can display some of these messages
or at least show them to the actual clients
or on the clients.
So now when I send a message to Brian,
then the chat server is going to record that.
And then it's going to take that list
and send it back to everybody who's registered in the list.
So what I need to do is be able to pick up that message type
coming back from the server.
Now, one thing we can assume is that the server will
be sending messages that are of the chat type.
And if that's the case, then I just need to receive them.
So here, let's go to when I receive.
And I'm going to say chat.
I'll get the ID and the message.
So that we can assume is going to be someone's username as
well as what they are saying.
And now the easiest possible way to do
this is just to kind of duplicate that on our side
and want to be in looks and have Ada say the message.
And so here, we would just say the message.
Well, probably what we want to do is something like this.
We want to do a join block here.
And we want to say that the ID, which is the username,
and then we put something like a colon and a space.
And then we open this up to add another block.
And then we display the message.
And let me just put it up there for five seconds.
And then I should be able to echo those messages back.
So now, when I send a message, it's
still going to go through the chat server.
It's still going to register on Brian's screen.
But then Brian's going to relay it
to everyone who's registered and then send it back.
And then I will pick up that return message and display it.
Let's try that.
So I will press space.
See, here we go, space.
What is your message?
Hello, can you hear me?
And voila, you see that the message came back to me.
So there's a lot more that you could do to build this out
and to display messages on your screen.
Probably you don't want to be picking up
your messages in a say block every time
because in a typical chat log, it's
going to be message after message underneath each other.
Maybe you put them in different colors.
You're in one color.
Everybody else is a different color.
There's lots of things you can do to build this out.
But Brian, I think it's been more than 20 minutes.
I think this is a good introduction to the client
server type of application that you can build with NetBlocks
and also to using those public role IDs as a way
to communicate across NetBlocks instances
without having to use a room or a role.
Yeah, I totally agree.
So thank you, everyone, and look forward
to seeing you in the next video.
All right, bye, everyone.
Bye.