Hi, everyone.
Welcome back to Programming for a Networked World.
We're going to continue our exploration of networking
concepts in Netsblocks today.
And we're going to do that by interacting very dynamically
and graphically with each other's programs.
So we're going to return to this concept of a room that
has roles.
And our goal today is to develop a shared whiteboard.
That is, we're going to make it possible for me
to write something on the stage,
and then for that to show up on Brian's computer,
and vice versa.
When he writes something on his stage,
it'll show up in my computer.
So you could think about it as a collaborative whiteboard.
And so to do this, we're going to go back
to that idea of using messages to pass content
to each other with particular message types.
And to get us all started on this,
let me pass over to Brian, who's going to show us,
first of all, how we even start drawing stuff on our screen.
All right.
Well, thank you, Cliff.
So as Cliff said, we're going to be starting
with this shared whiteboard example.
So much like our running dog example,
where we were sending some sort of data payload
that was relevant for the application,
so not just displaying, but for knowing what costumes are set,
or things like that, we're going to be seeing something similar
here with our shared whiteboard.
Now, as Cliff mentioned, we first
need to start by just, rather than jumping right
into this collaborative whiteboard, where we're both
drawing and seeing what each other draw on our screens,
we're going to simplify this problem,
or break it down anyway, into just trying to draw
on our screen by ourselves.
So I've got this new project here, this shared whiteboard.
And I might rename this sprite something like, I don't know,
my pen.
And this sprite is going to represent, again,
the pen that we're using to draw,
if you want to think of it that way.
So the first thing we need is that when
we're moving our mouse, our pen, or our drawing tool anyway,
it should be following our cursor.
So if we look at the motion category,
we have a block that's the go-to mouse pointer.
And if we click it, we can see the sprite disappears,
because it moves all the way off the stage,
right to where my cursor is, which
is, again, over this block.
So let's put this in a loop, a forever loop,
and see if we can see that it is, in fact,
following our cursor as we move it around.
We can see that it is.
Now, you'll notice, though, that when I'm, well,
we'll see more of this later.
But we'll see that it is staying right on top,
and I think just underneath my cursor, which
will come up in a moment here.
Now, we probably want our program
to start when the green flag is clicked.
And when the mouse is down, we probably want to draw.
And when it's released, we probably want to stop drawing.
So we can use an if block here.
So if the mouse is down, then we can draw or put our pen down.
So now if we try this, we click the green flag.
I push my mouse down, and I draw.
And you see that it actually is into drawing.
So this is kind of odd.
But if you take a close look, you'll
notice that when I let go of the cursor, there is no shadow.
But when I click, there's actually
a shadow behind my sprite.
So this is a common gotcha when you're
building this application.
And if you look over to your sprite,
we can see there's a draggable toggle right at the bottom.
And if we click that, now we can't pick up our sprite.
So since our sprite was following our cursor,
when we clicked, we actually clicked on it,
and we're moving our sprite around.
So now we can see that we are, in fact, drawing.
But of course, even when I let go of my mouse,
it's still drawing.
And that makes sense, because if we look at our code here,
we can see that we don't have any point in this code
where we actually pick our mouse back up,
or pick the pen back up, so it's always drawing.
If we right-click on the if block here, we can relabel.
This is a little tip to convert our if statement
into an if else.
So if the mouse isn't down, instead of doing the pen up,
we'll put it down.
Now we can clear the whiteboard by just clicking this block.
We actually might also want to clear it
every time we start a new, start drawing fresh, so to speak.
So now if we click, we can see that the program is,
if we click the green flag,
we see that our program is running,
our sprite is following our cursor.
When we click and put the mouse down,
or click our mouse and move it around,
we can see we are drawing.
And now if I release, I stop drawing.
So now we have a very simple drawing application.
We might want to make a couple little tweaks
because this pen does look a little funny
at this kind of 90 degree angle.
So maybe we want to, say, point in the direction of,
I don't know, maybe over here.
If we try this, now we can see that we have an indicator
that looks a little bit more natural.
All right, so this gives us our simplest program to start,
where we're actually able to draw on the screen.
So now we can start thinking a little bit more
about the networking components.
And the first thing that we'll do is actually
create a new role and invite Cliff to it.
So we can start adapting this
to be a distributed application.
Now, rather than just adding a new role
by clicking this plus button at the bottom,
we can actually click on our role and just duplicate it.
So Cliff will get a copy of all our code
and everything too, so role dupe.
Now I can invite Cliff over.
All right, I got Brian's invitation here.
So I'll accept, and as you know,
I'll just move things around
and I get that request to be a collaborator,
so I'll request that permission.
And when Brian grants that to me,
I can move things around, so that's fantastic.
Now, one thing you have to realize,
because this is a distributed application,
the green flag clicked.
That means that the process kicks off on your own computer.
But if you're working with a process
that's on someone else's computer,
that green flag won't have any effect.
You're in a separate process from them.
So you actually need to send a message
to indicate that your program is starting.
So you can't just rely on the green flag clicked
to kick off a process on both parts.
You need to do that explicitly.
So what we'll do here is we're going to pull this out
and we're going to say, when green flag clicked,
and then we're going to send a message over the network.
And let's just call this message.
We're going to make it very simple.
We're going to call it start.
And we don't want to have any fields, because we don't need
to have any fields for it, just a plain token, basically,
saying that our program is starting.
So when the green flag is clicked,
I am going to send message start.
And we're going to send it to just everyone in the room.
So we could set a particular role,
but we might want to add more people to the shared message
board.
So we're just going to have everyone
when this starts.
Now, we also need to handle this ourselves,
because if you just click like that,
you send the message and nothing happens.
So we do need to then also say, when I receive, start,
just like this, and then we'll pull these blocks back up.
So now we're kicking things off.
When this starts, I'll receive start,
and then I can start drawing.
And Brian can start drawing.
Anyone in the room can start drawing.
That is if we actually have messages that communicate
what should be drawn.
So for that part, let me just turn it back over to Brian
to talk about how to set it up so
that what you're writing on your screen
actually gets sent out as a message to others.
Well, thank you, Cliff.
So as Cliff mentioned, we need to have some way
to communicate not just when the program starts,
but also what should be drawn or what has been
drawn by the other person.
So to be able to share this information,
we need to have some message type that includes this data.
So we're going to make a new message type,
and we're going to call it, let's say, draw.
We can give it two fields, one which I'm calling Xs,
or just spelling Xs, and the other one which
is following the same approach that's Ys, so Ys.
So once we define this new message type,
now we just need to think about what exactly
should this data payload be.
So we know we added these two fields, Xs and Ys,
which we can think of as the X locations and Y locations
that we were drawing on.
So when we're drawing, so when our pen is down,
we can start sending these X and Y locations
that we are drawing.
The only tricky thing, though, and actually
before we jump into that, and we can
see that if we use these under the motion category,
this X position and Y position block,
this will tell us where our little indicator,
our kind of pen, is on the screen.
So we could just go through, and if we think about the process
before we write this code, we could just go through,
and when the mouse is down, so in other words,
when we're drawing, which we already
have an if statement that is capturing this condition,
we could just start collecting a small segment of line
that we drew, and then we could send it over
to the other people involved.
So let's give this a try.
So actually, before we jump into it this way,
we could make it one step even simpler.
And we could just keep track of what we drew
and then send it over once we're done drawing.
So we can just make some variables.
I'm just going to name them the same thing that we're naming
our field, so X's and Y's.
And when the mouse is down, these X's and Y's
are the list of X coordinates and Y coordinates to draw on,
can just start collecting the current location of your pen.
So in other words, if the mouse is down, we have pen down,
but then we'll also add our current X position
to our list of X positions to draw.
And similarly, add our current Y position to our list of Y's.
Now, like before, we're going to also
need to initialize, of course, these lists of X's and Y's.
So when the green flag is clear, or when the program starts,
set your X's and Y's to an empty list.
Now, you'll notice that I first started putting it
under the when green flag click, but then I
caught myself, because we really want it
when the program starts, which could be when I click
the green flag, or when Cliff clicks the green flag,
and then I just receive the start message.
So now we have this simple first pass, where when we're drawing,
we're recording this list of X's and Y's.
And then as soon as the pen comes up,
then we could just draw or share whatever
we drew in that little batch.
So now we would share this by sending a draw message
to Cliff or to the other roles.
That includes your X's and Y's.
Now, we probably don't want to send this if they're empty.
So we probably just want to make sure
that we actually did draw something,
or else every time we don't have our pen down,
we'll just be sending a bunch of messages.
So we can add another if statement in here
that's checking to see if we have any X's or Y's in the list.
All right.
So we check to see if the length of our X's,
or we could check with the Y's, they should be the same length,
is greater than 0.
And if that's the case, then we're
going to send this draw message to the others in the room.
All right.
So now at this point, when we're drawing,
now, it'll put the pen down and should draw it on our screen.
And then as soon as we stop drawing something,
it should send the drawing that we just made over
to the other people in the room.
And then, of course, we should be
drawing that on our own screen.
So with that, I will kick it over to Cliff
to implement the remote pen, or the pen of the other person
using this whiteboard, that should be then drawing
or handling these draw messages.
So I believe that I have at least a similar version
to what Ryan coded on his end.
As you say, as long as it has the same functionality,
we're good.
But now the thing is, why do I need to create another sprite?
Well, I could handle his messages coming over
in my same sprite, but the effect
would be that we'd be fighting over that sprite.
I would be trying to write, and then messages
would be coming in saying that Brian wants to write there.
And we would probably be bouncing around or struggling
to take control of that sprite.
And that's not what we want.
We actually want a collaborative whiteboard.
So in order to do that, I'm going
to create a new sprite over here.
And I'm going to call this one, let's call it remote pen.
How about that?
And in remote pen, I'm going to then
want to capture the messages that
are coming from the pen that Brian is using
and then draw them on my board.
So I can actually reuse a lot of what I've got here.
So let me just pull this part over.
Oops, am I going to be able to pull over and leave it?
Oh, yeah.
Yeah, there we go.
OK.
OK, so we don't need the start here,
because we're already going to be starting.
But what we do need is to handle the message that's
coming from Brian that he's wanting us to draw.
So when I receive draw, then I've got my x's and y's.
We don't need to set those anymore.
And so I've got my x's and y's.
And what we need to do now is just
And what we need to do now is just to draw them.
And I also didn't need to capture the information,
because presumably, we've already got that information.
But we don't want the forever block,
because we only want to do this for the amount of time
that Brian has data in the payload that he sent us.
So for that reason, we'll use another kind of loop here.
Let's go to get a loop here.
And we'll just repeat for the length of the x's,
because they always come in pairs of x's and y's.
So I can duplicate this here.
And so there we go.
So for the length of the x's, we're going to repeat this.
I'm going to put the pin down.
And then we're going to go to, now, the question is,
where do you want to put the pin down?
If you put the pin down before you get started,
you'll have these kind of jump lines
that go from where you are right now,
or where Brian left off, to where he's drawing.
We don't want to do that.
We want to actually just put the pin down
after we get the initial starting point.
So we probably don't need this now.
So we'll start at length.
We'll repeat this for the length of our iterations
that we get from draw.
And now we just need to do the drawing.
So we'll go to this x and y-coordinate here.
And there.
And then at the end of this, we just take the pin up.
And that's under pin, of course.
It's a different green.
There we go.
And that should take the pin up.
I think that's all we need.
Let's see.
Let's give it a whirl.
Let's give it a try.
All right, so I'm going to actually take these watchers
off, too, which just make it look nice.
All right, so I'm going to hit the green flag.
That should start for both of us.
You can see that messages are coming
through, lots of messages.
We are not drawing on my end yet.
So there are a few problems.
As you can see, we have this little red speech bubble
on Cliff's screen right here.
And that's showing that there are
a lot of messages being sent.
So if we look back at our code, we
can see that if the length of the x's is greater than 0,
we send this draw message.
But we don't actually clear the list of x's.
And we are also not handling the,
we need to iterate through this in a way that
actually handles each item in the list and then clears it.
Yeah, exactly.
So we need to.
There's some problems on both ends, I would say.
Yeah, there are.
But debugging is a natural part of it.
Debugging is good.
All right, so why don't you debug your side first?
So if we look on our side, we can see that we just
need to set the x's and the y's to this empty list.
And that should take care of it.
Now, on Cliff's side, you can see
he's got this big message queue buildup.
He should be able to just right click, I believe,
on the message handler.
Or maybe it's just regular click on the dialog.
Can you click on the little dialog?
I always forget.
There we go.
OK.
You can clear the message queue.
So now we don't have to worry about actually handling
those thousands of messages.
That's actually a good thing to know,
because that will happen frequently
if you have messages piling up.
And so the way that you saw us clear them,
it's important to understand.
And also, what we see here, then,
is I need to, when I'm getting the length of this list,
I actually need to then iterate through it each item at a time
and then draw it.
So probably, rather than the repeat block,
since I need to actually keep track
of where I am in the iteration, we
should probably use a for loop.
So let's do this.
So for 1 to the length of xs is going to be better.
And then we're going to have to grab from our list the item
that corresponds here.
So we can duplicate this.
And then we're going to want to go here to each of these
in turn.
Make sure we get the x and the y in the right place.
There we go.
And then we put the pin down here so that we start writing.
And at the end of it, we take the pin up.
All right.
So we'll give it another try.
See if that works better.
All right.
So now I draw something.
And as soon as I'm done drawing, it draws on my side.
And no messages are piling up either.
So I think we cleared those two bugs.
That's fantastic.
Now, there is a lot more that you
can do with this distributive whiteboard.
On my end, it should be the case that if I'm drawing,
let's see.
So we do need to fix that bug on this side.
Yeah, we have not fixed it.
And so I'm piling up those messages here.
So that might be something that we could do together.
Or you could, again, look at this code
and see where you need to fix that.
Basically, you need to make sure that you're
emptying these lists at a certain point.
Otherwise, your lists are just going to increase in size.
And you're just going to continually send these
messages.
So we need to empty our lists.
And there are other things that you
can do to maximize performance.
We're not going to probably get into it in this video.
But one thing that you could do, for example,
is send over lists of a certain size
so that you don't send each particular point
as a single item over the internet.
Because, again, there's a lot of latency involved.
Your messages may get piled up.
It might be better to send reliable chunks.
And the size of those chunks may depend
on what your network conditions are like.
So that's something you might want to experiment with.
But Brian, any other final thoughts before we wind up?
OK, so basically, one extension to this
is that currently, you can see that we're only
sending the drawings once they're complete.
So it might be nice to actually send drawings
while they're being drawn so that I don't finish my drawing
and then it shows up.
You could actually see me in the process of drawing
while I'm drawing it.
So if we wanted to do something like this,
we could actually start breaking the drawing into smaller chunks
and not waiting until the pen has come up
before we send it.
There are other nice features that
might be nice to add, like selecting your pen color
and, of course, synchronizing this across both devices.
Similarly, clearing the screen and synchronizing that as well
would be another kind of feature that would be nice to have.
All right, but I think we'll leave
that to you as an exercise.
We'll put some of that information in the comments
if you want to tackle those and maybe look at projects
where those features are implemented.
But for now, at least you get the idea
of how you can work collaboratively with two
sprites to develop a shared whiteboard.
And you also saw, by way of our errors,
what happens when something goes wrong in message passing
and how to both diagnose that error
and then to clear it from your program
so you can continue programming.
For sure.
So thanks, everyone, for joining us.
And we'll see you in our next video.