All right.
Welcome back, everyone, to Programming for a Network
World.
Today, we're going to be exploring
the topic of recursion.
Recursion is sometimes considered a difficult topic,
but I want to show in this video that it's really not
so bad at all.
So ready to explore recursion?
Ready to explore recursion?
Oh, did I say that already?
Let's get going.
OK, here's what we're going to do today.
We're going to build a project that computes factorials.
So for those of you that remember factorials,
factorials are the product of an integer
combined with all the integers that came before it.
So for example, a factorial of 3 is 3 times 2 times 1,
which is 3 times 2 is 6, and 6 times 1 is 6.
So the factorial of 3 is 6.
We're going to make two programs that compute factorials.
We're going to do it the traditional way with just
a loop, and then we're going to redo it
as a recursive function or using a block that
employs recursion.
All right.
So how do we do it the traditional way?
Let's get started with that.
So I'm going to make a block over here,
and I'm going to say make a block.
I'm going to go over to the operator here,
and then we're going to pick a reporter.
I'm going to call this, let's call it loop factorial of n,
and we'll create that.
Then I'm going to click here to make n an input that
takes a number.
OK.
And that should be good.
So say OK.
I'm going to bring this over here
and open it up a little bit more so we can
see this whole scripting area.
All right.
So the first thing that we need to do is make a variable.
So let's make a variable here called result.
That's going to be the result that we pass out
of this function or that we report.
And then we want to start a loop.
So let's go up to Control, and let's get a for loop here.
Now, we want to loop as many times
as there are integers in a number that
are previous in the sequence going down to 1.
So from here, we'll just count up
because this is commutative.
We can go either direction.
We're going to count from 1 to n.
So n will be, for example, 3.
Then we'll do 1, 2, and 3.
OK.
And now, we just need to think about what we want to compute.
So we need to get a variable set block here.
I'm going to set this.
Now, we're going to set the result to in here.
We're going to get an operator to i,
which is going to be 1, 2, 3 times result.
Now, if you look at this right here,
we're going to have a bug because result is going
to be initialized to 0.
So we need to remember that if we're
going to initialize it to 1, we need to tell it so explicitly.
So we're going to say set result to 1.
Otherwise, everything multiplied by 0 would just end up being 0.
And then at the end of this, we want to report.
Let's see, under Control, we want to report our result.
All right, so let's get that and pull down Result.
And that should be it.
So let's give it a try.
So now, remember, it disappears because it's now
under Custom, loop factorial.
And we can try 3.
And the answer should be 6.
And it is.
And 5 should be 120.
You go up to 10, and it gets to be a much bigger number.
But that is the correct result.
So we built a function that computes factorials.
Great.
Now, how do we do this in a recursive way?
So when you're thinking about recursion,
the fundamental idea is that you create a block that calls
itself as part of its solution.
And in order to do that, you need
to make sure that your recursive block has two cases.
One's called the base case, and the other
is called the recursive case.
And you want to make sure that when you're computing,
that your recursive case is tending towards the base case
and will eventually reach it.
Because the base case controls when the recursion ends.
And if you never get to the base case,
then you'll just keep going over and over in a circle.
And eventually, your program will produce something
called a stack overflow or some kind of error
that runs out of memory or space.
OK, that might seem a little abstract.
So let's just put it together in a practical example.
So we'll make a block here.
And we're going to take this.
It's going to be an operator again.
And we'll call this recursive factorial of n.
And it will be the same as the other.
We're just going to turn n into an input for a number.
Let's get a number here.
There we go.
All right.
And again, let's just make a little bit more space
and start building this up.
So again, with a base case and a recursive case,
the best way to handle this is probably
with an if-then expression or an if-then-else.
So let's grab an if-then-else.
And the first thing that we're going to test
is the base case.
So the base case is when we reach 1.
We don't want to go into 0, because if we multiply,
as I said before, anything by 0, it's
going to be 0 as a result. And we don't want
to get into negative numbers.
We probably should be testing the input on the way
in to make sure that the input to start with is not negative.
But we're trying to keep this example simple.
If you feel like adding that on, that would be a great exercise.
If n is equal to 1, then we're going
to do something, which is we're just going to report.
Here we go.
Oh, I keep going to the wrong tabs.
OK.
We want to go to report n.
Now, you could also just report 1, because if n equals 1,
then you know the answer is 1.
But to keep it kind of nice and clean, we're going to report n.
So this is the base case.
So else is going to be the recursive case.
And I might even just make comments here.
So let's just add something here.
Let's say a comment.
And we can put it right there.
And we can say base case, just to make that totally clear.
Then we can make another comment and put it down here.
Whoops.
I guess it's harder to do with the else.
So we'll just put it down here in recursive case.
OK.
So base case.
And then actually, the recursive case is here.
So we'll kind of just put it off to the side.
That's the base case.
This is going to be the recursive case inside the else.
So the recursive case has to call this function again,
but with different inputs.
So what would that look like?
So here, we're going to do report again.
So we're going to report.
And that's going to help us to call this function.
Now, you say, OK, I want to call this function again.
But how do I reach up and call it?
Well, you can go to custom and actually pull this block back
in.
So we're going to do that here.
This allows us now to connect a recursive case.
Good.
And we're going to say recursive factorial of.
And here, what is it?
It's not n any longer.
It's going to be n minus 1.
So let's do that.
Because we're trying to move towards or converge
on the base case.
But there's one more thing that we need to do.
So here we go.
Recursive case of n minus 1.
We also need to multiply n times all the other numbers that
are in the line of integers until we get to 1.
And so to do that, we're going to take this multiplication
here, going to multiply this, and we're
going to multiply this by n.
So again, you can see this here.
There we go.
So we have the base case.
If n equals 1, then we just report n.
Otherwise, we report n.
That could be 3 times the recursive factorial of 2.
And then that will recurse.
And again, you'll have the same question.
Is it going to be the base case?
No, this time it's 2.
So then it's going to be 2 times the recursive factorial of 1.
And then it's going to go through again and say,
is it 1?
Yes.
And so it reports 1.
And then it calculates 1 times 2 times 3.
And you get your answer of 6.
So that's how recursion is done.
And let's just see if it works in practice.
So we're going to go over here to Custom again.
We're going to bring over the recursive factorial.
And I'm going to try again 3 just to test it out.
It should be 6.
It is.
Let's test it out as 5.
Should be 120.
It is.
And then we can test.
Let's try 10.
Now, you might say, OK, these are two ways
of doing the same thing.
Why would I even bother with doing recursion?
And the answer is it depends on the context.
In almost all the cases, with some very small sort
of edge cases, you can always turn a recursive operation
into a loop and vice versa.
But sometimes it's more efficient to calculate
something recursively.
And sometimes it's even easier to program it
because you're kind of focused on the logic of the problem
rather than the looping operation
and keeping track of the state of all those interim values.
You kind of let the computer do that for you
when you're doing recursion.
And depending on your programming environment,
doing a recursive function may actually
be faster and more efficient.
So let's just test this out here very unscientifically.
But I'm going to take a big number.
Let's try 50 for both of these.
And you'll see a noticeable lag, for example,
when I run this first one.
Calculates, and then we get it in scientific notation.
But you can see that it took maybe a second.
And we do the same thing here, and it instantly reports.
I don't even know if we can get up to 100.
Let's see if we'll go that high.
You can see that it probably took about two seconds
to calculate that.
And again, with this function, it's more or less instantaneous.
And we could keep going with that.
Again, we're going to hit an upper limit where it won't
be able to calculate this at all.
We got to infinity.
And we probably will reach infinity faster here.
So express train to infinity.
There you go.
But the point is, within NETs blocks,
sometimes recursion will produce faster results
than the traditional way of doing things
with looping structures.
All right, so that is our video for today.
I hope that was a useful introduction to recursion.
And I will see you in our next video.