Hi everyone. Welcome back to our series on programming for a networked world.
Today we're talking about lists. We all have experience making lists.
Every day I add items to my list of things to do.
For example, I added a reminder to make a video today about lists.
So, now I can cross that item off my to-do list.
Lists in Nextbox function in a similar fashion.
Nextbox allows programmers to create lists, add items to lists,
find items on lists, and remove items from lists.
Lists also help programmers to manage related items of information.
Ready to recreate your virtual to-do list in Nextbox?
Let's make some lists together.
Lists are a fundamental data structure in Nextbox.
Lists come in all shapes and sizes, but we'll begin by covering the simplest
form of list. That is a one-dimensional list.
A one-dimensional list is a fancy name for a list that just contains a
sequence of things like numbers, strings, sprites, etc.
We can create a list of this simple sort by
going over to the variable palette and pulling out the list block.
In that input slot we can just put, let's see,
script a video. And if we want to add something else I can
expand this block and say
film a video. If you click on the list block now
you'll notice that we have a pop-up. It gives us the items in the list back
next to the numbers 1 and 2. So, as you can imagine,
those are the first and second items in the list.
In some languages the first item in the list is indexed as 0
and the second item as 1. In Nextbox we follow the more intuitive system
of numbering the first item as 1 and the second as 2
and so on and so forth. But that is called the
index of the item. It gives you a number by which you can look up that item
in the list. Adding items to our list by just expanding the list block
and adding them manually will get boring over time.
We'd rather have our program do this for us, right? Not just do it by hand.
Fortunately we can add new items programmatically as well.
So, for instance, we can add a third item,
say like edit video to our list, using the add to list block.
We'll type in the item that we want to add to our list and then we'll bring
down the list and hopefully it'll all work. Let's take a
look. So the four blocks that you see down here
are command blocks that mutate lists. That is, they'll change the information
contained in a list. And the four blocks, as you can see, are
add, delete, insert, and replace. We're going to try
all four of them, but let's start with the add block.
So I can bring over the add block here and
this little slot here with the alternating red and white
is the slot for the list. And then I can add
a thing. Let's give it a name. Let's say
produce video. So I can type that in, produce
video, and then I can click on it. Ah, but nothing happened.
Why didn't anything happen? Well, this is a command block
and it mutated the list, but it didn't show us the result.
So in order for us to see what the result is, we need to create a variable
first to contain our list. So I will create a variable called to do.
Let's go up to the top here and make a variable.
And I'll call the variable to do. There we go.
And now what I'm going to do is I'm going to bring over this set block
and I'm going to drop this list in and I'll call it to do.
And now I can take that reference here and put it down here. So you can see
if I bring up the watcher now, after I set it,
I've got two items in my list. But when I add
another item, it will appear as the third item in the list.
And there you go. So I've just mutated the list by adding a third
item to it. So now the list contains three items.
So let's try our hand at the three other blocks that mutate lists.
The delete block, the replace block, and the insert block. These blocks all
work with the index of the items in the list.
To use them, you need to know where the item you want to remove or insert or
replace falls in the list. So for example, if I have finished the
script for the video, I should delete that from my to-do list.
I can use the delete block to do that. And since I know that that was the first
item on my list, it's very easy to get the index. It's
just index one. So let's try that. I'll go over here
and bring in delete. Delete item one of. Let's duplicate this to-do list.
And I'll bring it down here. Put it in the slot. Delete item one.
You can see I've finished now scripting the video.
The second thing that I need to do is let's add a third thing. I want to produce
the video. I've got that. So let's say upload it to YouTube. So let's say
upload video to YouTube. How about that? Spell that correctly.
Okay, so I'm going to add that, but I don't want to add it as my first item, so
that's not the right place to put it. I'm going to insert it now.
If I can get that text again so I don't have to retype it all.
And put it down here. And I'm going to insert that as number
three. So I'll put it at the end of the list. So there we go.
Oh, yes, if you don't put the list in, you will see that error message.
So I'll put the list in and insert it. And there it is. Upload video.
Okay, oh, misspelled. So I misspelled it. That's actually helpful because now I
want to replace it with something that's spelled correctly.
So let's do that. So I'm going to take this
replace item, and I want to replace number three.
And I want to use the same list. So I'll duplicate the list here.
Put it in. And again, I'll click and copy this. But before I change it, I want to
change this O to a P so it's spelled correctly. So you see we
have UOLOAD. And if I click on this now,
oh, don't need it connected with another block. If I click on this now,
you can see that it replaced it to upload video.
So with the combination of these four blocks,
you can make lists contain any type of information you want,
and you can keep it updated in real time as information
in the program changes. So keeping track of information using lists is an
extremely common task in Nest Blocks. Practically every application you write
will involve the use of lists. Many times it will involve the use of
multiple lists. In this video, we saw how to create a
one-dimensional list and mutate it by adding, deleting,
inserting, and changing items. But lists can do more than store your
to-do items. In the next video, we'll explore how to
use two-dimensional lists to store and explore tabular information.
But that's it for today. If you want to do something for extra credit,
then try building your own to-do list in Nest Blocks.
And don't forget to add watch the next video in this series
to that to-do list. Thanks very much, and see you next time.