Hi.
Welcome back to Programming for a Network World.
Today, we're going to be talking about the broadcast block.
The broadcast block allows you to send messages
across projects and let those messages be picked up
by other sprites or blocks.
So when you think about broadcasting in daily life,
if I want to broadcast something to the people around me,
I might shout, here, here.
And then they would look to me to see what I was talking about.
So in Nets blocks, broadcasts work in much the same way.
You can broadcast a message, and then other blocks
will pick up that message and be able to respond to it.
Ready to try out the broadcast block?
Let's get started.
OK, so to get going, we're going to set up
a very simple exercise of just sending a broadcast message
and then receiving that broadcast.
But we're going to do it across two sprites.
So the way we'll begin is we'll set up a message
that Ada will send out.
And if I go over here to the Control palette
and I bring over Broadcast, you see, oh, there we go.
Let's bring over Broadcast.
It has a dropdown.
And I can drop it down, and I can say New.
And it's going to ask me for a message name.
The message name is basically a bare symbol.
It's anything that you want to give it.
And that's what the receiver of the broadcast
will get when the message is sent out.
So it doesn't have any content beyond its name.
That's why I call it a symbol.
So I will just say Broadcast Hello.
And let's put that.
And you'll see that I've got now my Hello message.
And so let's just put When Space is Clicked to get it
a little bit more interesting.
Now, if I just click this right now,
you'll see that it activates, but nothing happens.
And that's simply because we've broadcast this message,
but there's no corresponding receiver
to pick up that message.
So let's bring in another sprite to pick up our message.
I'm going to go over here, and I'm going to create.
Let's see.
We've got to go over here to create a sprite first.
And there it is.
Let's give it a costume.
So I'm going to go over to Costumes.
Always takes a while to open up Costumes.
And there's Alonzo.
And we'll bring up Alonzo on the stage a little bit.
Now, we want Alonzo to receive that message
and then do something in response.
So now we're working inside of Alonzo's script area.
And there is a corresponding block
called When I Receive.
So this hat block can have a dropdown here
that shows it can respond to any message.
So anytime anything happens that's broadcast,
it can respond to it.
Or it can respond to particular types of broadcast messages.
In this case, we're going to use the Hello message.
And so when Alonzo receives the broadcast from Ada,
then Alonzo will respond with whatever
we put under this hat block.
And in this case, why don't we go to a Say block.
And we'll say, hello to you too.
OK.
So now we have a very simple program.
We'll start it off with Ada.
And we'll press the Space key.
And voila, you see.
We'll try it again.
There it is.
Hello to you too.
So Ada broadcast this message hello.
And then inside of our Alonzo script,
we see when I receive hello, say hello to you too.
Now, the way that you use broadcast very often in programs
is to coordinate events that are taking place.
It's very often used, for example, in games.
So when you're working with a game, for example,
you might want to set a condition in which
if two sprites collide with each other,
then the game is over.
And you broadcast to everything else in the game
this game over event.
So that's a very common way of setting this up.
And we can try that ourselves here.
So let's move our scripts off.
And we're going to start again afresh.
Here we go.
And we will set up.
Let's do a little change of our characters.
We'll say goodbye to Ada.
And we'll change Alonzo's costume
into a rocket ship, how about?
So let's go down to costumes again.
And let's take a look.
There's a rocket ship here somewhere.
There's a robot.
That's not too bad.
We could go for that if we can't find the rocket.
Ah, spaceship.
We did get it.
So let's bring that in.
There's a spaceship.
Now, and we want to remove this costume.
So we've got a spaceship.
And let's set up some more sprites, or at least one more.
So we'll create a new one.
And let's give this one a costume
that we create ourselves.
So we'll go over here to paint.
And I'm going to just take this circle like this.
And then maybe we'll color it a little bit differently.
Here we go.
OK.
Now, this is going to be a very simple game.
And you're going to have to expand on this
to make it interesting.
But what we'll do for this sprite, which
we'll call rock or asteroid or something like that,
we'll have this come down from the top of the screen.
And then the rocket will need to avoid it.
And if the rocket collides with it,
then we're going to broadcast the game over event.
OK.
So we're going to take this asteroid.
And we're going to go to a scripting area.
And when we start the game, when the green flag is clicked,
we want to move it to the very top of the screen
and hide it off screen.
All right.
So let's do that.
Hide here.
We're going to find under Looks.
There we go.
We're going to hide it.
We're going to go to, let's say, coordinate x is 0.
And this will be negative 200.
Let's just try that out.
And there we go.
OK, so it's off the screen.
Let's have it go down and see if it can collide with our rocket.
OK.
So we'll take the next thing we want to do is, OK,
we're going to have it glide to a particular direction.
And we're going to have that direction be chosen at random.
So we need to go to Operators and look at Random.
Pick Random here.
OK.
So we'll have it glide.
And let's set our initial time of five seconds.
And then let's have it glide to someplace
on the bottom of the screen, 150, let's say, 200.
OK.
And between this and this, let's just try it out
and see how it works.
And we need to show it, too.
OK, so let's try this.
Let's see how that works.
Oh, we've got it coming from the wrong direction, which
could be a challenge.
So let's switch these.
So this will be 200.
And then we'll try negative 200.
Let's try that.
OK.
So we've got our asteroid coming down.
And it's not going down quite far enough.
We want it to be off screen.
So let's go to negative 250.
And now we just want to put this into some kind of loop,
right, so that we have new asteroids coming down
every time.
And we need to make sure that they change a little bit more
in their direction.
So let's do 150, negative 150 to 150.
Let's see if that works better.
This should make our asteroid do a little bit more
interesting paths at random, going in different directions.
It makes the game a little bit more interesting.
There we go.
And we'll make it a little bit faster.
OK.
So let's put this into a loop.
And we're going to do, let's do a forever block.
So that's down here.
And there we go.
OK, let's just test this out.
It should just keep going.
So we get down to the bottom.
And it goes up to the top again.
And it's going to be picking different directions.
OK.
So we got that piece going.
And now we need to give some controls to the rocket.
So let's get over to the rocket.
And here, with the rocket, we basically
want to respond to the event of moving left and right.
We basically want to respond to the event of moving
left and right.
So when the key is pressed, in this case,
let's just assign this to the left arrow.
Then we want to move, let's see, we'll say, change x here.
That's probably the easiest block to use.
So that's our x-coordinate.
And we're going to change it by negative 5.
Let's just test that out.
So it's moving to the left.
And now if we want to move it to the right,
we can duplicate this, drop this down here,
and put it to the right.
There we go.
OK, so now we've got controls here.
I've got to change this to 5, because otherwise we're
just moving the same direction.
So now we've got controls.
We can move our rocket back and forth.
So in a way, we're ready to play our game, right?
So if we start this with the green flag,
I can move and try to avoid this.
Oh, not so good.
Let me try that again.
Got to move faster.
There we go.
Get back to the center.
Whoa.
OK, so we can play our game.
But you notice there's one problem here.
I mean, to make this a full-fledged game,
there's probably lots of things that we want to add.
But there's one very significant problem,
namely, when this asteroid comes into proximity
with the rocket, nothing happens.
So we need to detect that event.
And then we need to broadcast this game over event
to show that the game has, in fact,
ended when the two objects collide.
So to do that, let's go over to here.
We're back again inside of our rocket sprite.
And we're going to do a sensing block.
And we've got this touching.
So we can drop down, and we can say when.
So this is just detecting that it's touching.
So it's not touching right now.
That's false.
But if we click on it again when they are touching, it's true.
OK, so we'll do another event here under Control.
And this will be when touching.
So when that occurs, we're going to broadcast game over.
So now, let's go back and get a broadcast block.
So we're going to broadcast here.
And we're going to make a new message.
We're going to call it game over.
Here we go.
So now, you'll see, when they're touching,
it will broadcast game over.
But we haven't set anything up on the receiver side yet.
So in this case, if we're running this,
the message is broadcast as soon as the asteroid
touches the rocket.
But nothing stops because we haven't set up
the receiver on the side.
So we need to set up the receiver here.
And let's just do that.
When I receive over here, game over.
Now, we just want to do something
that's going to stop that.
So you'll see that down here, there is a stop all.
And so that will stop the sprite from doing its forever loop.
And so in this case, when the two objects collide,
then it should broadcast game over.
And the other sprite should receive that message.
And stop all.
OK, let's try it.
So here we go.
I'm avoiding.
Oh, I didn't avoid it well enough.
The game is over.
Let's try it again.
Oh, oh.
All right, let's try it one more time.
Here we go.
I just cannot avoid it.
I really want to try to avoid this.
OK, I avoided one successfully.
That's good.
Avoiding another, just barely.
And oh, oh.
It collided.
So you see now that these two sprites
are communicating to each other by broadcasting
these symbols that are picked up.
And then you can respond to those messages that
are broadcast appropriately.
All right, that's it for this time.
We're going to be diving into more complex messages
next time that Nets Blocks enables.
And we'll see you in our next video.
Thank you.