Hi, everyone.
Welcome back to Programming for a Network World.
Today, we're going to solve the hardest
problem in computer science.
That is FizzBuzz.
I'm just kidding, actually.
FizzBuzz is a children's game.
And we'll show in this episode how
to solve it using the tools that you already
have in your toolkit.
But FizzBuzz gained a reputation about 10 years ago
of being a difficult problem for aspiring programmers
to solve during coding interviews.
So ready to put on your interviewing hat
and learn how to solve FizzBuzz?
Let's get started.
So let's review the rules of FizzBuzz.
FizzBuzz is basically a substitution game.
So you're going to count from 1 to 15.
And whenever a number is cleanly divisible by 3,
that is divisible by 3 without remainder, you'll say Fizz.
If it's divisible by 5 without remainder, you'll say Buzz.
And if it's divisible by both 3 and 5, then you'll say FizzBuzz.
Now, let's start by just establishing
a loop that will have a counter to count
those numbers as we go through.
So we can do that by going over here to Control.
And let's go over and bring out the block
we've already used called Repeat and change this to 15.
And then let's make a variable that we'll
put on top of this under Variables.
And we'll make one called Count.
And then let's set Count over here to 1.
So we'll start at 1.
And then as we go through, we're going
to change Count by 1 each time.
Now, you'll see if I click on this
that it will actually reach 16.
But that's OK because that final increment will not
be used in our program.
It'll just be the final state of the counter.
But it's something to be aware of when you're programming.
OK.
Now, the next thing is to set up our Boolean conditionals.
So let's go over to Operators again.
And we're going to pull in our conditionals.
So the question is, we know that we need this Boolean operator.
It's something equal to something else.
And we know that we want to test Count.
But the question is, what are we testing Count?
And what are we saying it should be equal to?
Well, we know that you can divide a number,
say 9 divided by 3.
And that's going to give you 3.
But how can you say 9 divided by 3 has no remainder?
If you remember from elementary school,
there's something called modular arithmetic.
And the idea is use what's called a modulus operator.
And you can perform the same operation, 9 modulus 3.
And it will give you the remainder.
So let's pull that out here.
And here's the modulus operator, shortened to mod.
And so we can say 9 and 3.
And it will say 0, because there's no remainder.
Now, if we'd said, for example, 10, let's change it to that,
mod 3, we should get 1, because there is a remainder.
So OK, we've got that working.
But this is reporting an actual value.
We wanted to report a Boolean here.
So let's put it in this.
And we're going to take this 10 out and put the count there.
And we're going to say this is equal to 0.
So that will be our first condition.
And let's just duplicate this.
And we're going to put 5 in for this one.
Now, how do we test 3 and 5?
Well, we could say that mathematically,
anything that's divisible by both 3 and by 5,
there's a way to test that to see if it's divisible by 15.
But if we wanted to use the Boolean operators,
we could do this by just bringing out the and block,
taking these two conditions.
Let's duplicate them here, putting 1 on one side
and putting 1 on the other side.
And there we go.
So now we have fizz.
If this is going to be true, that will be fizz.
This will be buzz.
And this will be fizzbuzz.
All right, now how do we integrate these into our program?
Well, we need to use conditional expressions.
These are expressions that allow us to do something differently
if a certain Boolean condition reports that it's true.
And we have two options here.
We can use if or we can use if then else.
Now, you might be tempted just to reach for the if block
because we want to say if it's, for example, divisible by 3,
then we should have a to say.
Let's go to looks here.
We should have a to say fizz.
And otherwise, let's go down here.
a should just say the number.
So let's grab that number, put it over here.
Now, I'm going to run this to 4.
And the answer should be 1, 2, fizz, 4.
But you'll see that that doesn't quite work.
So 1, 2, fizz, 3, 4.
So what's wrong?
Well, the problem is that this Boolean conditional,
when it passes, does indeed produce fizz.
But it falls through to the expression or the statement
below.
And so that's a problem.
We need to make sure that if fizz is reported,
if this Boolean condition is true,
then we don't actually say the number.
So to do that, we're going to have to pull this back out.
Let me do that.
Put these things back in.
And we're going to change this to an if then else.
So let me grab that over here.
And let's just put these back together.
So that's still a condition.
But now, if that condition is met, then it will do this.
Otherwise, if it's not met, then it's
going to do this part right here.
And the change stays outside this
because we still want to increment each time we go
through.
So that should be good.
And it should solve our problem of 1, 2, 3, 4.
Let's see.
1, 2, fizz, 4.
Perfect.
So let's stop there.
Now, how do we integrate the next one?
Well, that also needs to have an if then else.
But where do we place it?
Let's put the condition in first.
So what we want to do is we want to test this
after we test the 3.
So we're going to just drop this in right here.
And now we see that we've got this else we don't need.
We can put it right there.
And we've got a spot here to put in another say block.
Let's do that.
And we're going to say buzz.
Now, it should be the same thing.
When we count up to 5, it should be 1, 2, fizz, 4, buzz.
Let's see.
1, 2, fizz, 4, buzz.
Perfect.
OK.
Now, the last one is the most complicated one.
I'm going to just move this out of the way
so we don't get confused by this if block hanging around.
And the question is, where does this one fit?
We could put it at the end here after testing for 3 and 5.
And that might be the natural way you think about it.
But if you think about the logic of that, we'd have a problem.
Because by definition, anything that's divisible by 3
will be met before we test whether it's
divisible by 3 and 5.
And the same thing, anything that's divisible by 5,
the condition that is divisible by 5
will be met before we get to whether it's
divisible by 3 and 5.
So we need to actually place this at the top.
This is the first condition that we need to check.
And we're going to do that by, again, grabbing this,
grabbing this whole block, putting it into the else,
putting this here, making sure we
get the change that stays on the right part of it,
and then dropping this here.
OK.
So it should look like this.
And then at the top here, we're going to use looks.
And we're going to say, again, fizz buzz.
OK.
Now, I think we're ready to go through the whole circuit.
Let's just put a nice hat block on the top
so that we have the green flag is clicked.
That looks great.
And are we ready to go?
Let's test it out.
All right.
Here we go.
1, 2, fizz, 4, buzz, fizz, 7, 8, fizz, buzz, 11, fizz, 13, 14,
and fizz, buzz.
And then it stops.
All right.
So there you have it.
So today, we've learned several things.
We've learned how to use Boolean operators in practice.
We've seen how to differentiate when
you need to use a conditional if or a conditional if-then-else.
And we've also learned about how to use modular arithmetic
and the modulus operator in NetsBlocks programs.
All right.
You've already come a long way in this course.
And I look forward to seeing you in the next episode.
Thank you very much.