Hi everyone. Welcome back to Programming for a Networked World.
Today, we're going to talk about another way of processing lists.
Sometimes you come across very long lists,
and it becomes tedious to use a for loop to iterate through all the items.
So, in this particular video, we're going to talk about an alternative
to looping through lists when you want to process every item in a list.
So, ready to develop your superpowers when it comes to crunching lists?
Let's get started.
Okay, we're going to be talking today about map, keep, and combine.
These three blocks provide really powerful abstractions for working with lists.
These blocks take a particular operation, or more generally speaking, a function,
and apply it to each item in the list in turn.
Let me bring out the map block so we can talk about it in practice.
The map block, as you see, has two slots.
It has a ring where we put an operator, and then it has a slot for the list.
And what it's going to do is apply the operation that's in the ring
to each item in the list in turn, and then return a new list to you.
That may sound a little abstract, so let's try something in practice to see how it works.
I'm going to take over this numbers from 1 to 10 block,
and as you know, if I click on this, it will create numbers from 1 to 10.
That's pretty straightforward, and I'm going to drop this into our list slot.
Now, if we just use it like it is, then you'll see that with nothing in the ring,
it simply returns the list back to us.
So here you can see that it just returned 1 to 10.
But the magic of the map block is that we can take an operator
and drop it into that slot.
So now let's imagine that what I want to do is to double each of the items in the list.
So we would just say times 2 here, and then, you know,
we have to keep the first space open for each item.
So 1 times 2 is 2, 2 times 2 is 4, and so forth.
The problem is that we don't want to go iteratively through this list,
select each item, and put it into that empty slot.
What we'd like to do is have this block take care of that for us.
So the magic of the block is that by leaving that slot open,
it will simply put in or interpolate each item in the list into that open slot
and then perform the operation.
So you can see now that if I click on this,
I get a new list back with the same number of items,
but each of the items has doubled.
So that's fantastic, right?
Now, what if you wanted to filter a list?
That is, take some type of Boolean operator and apply it to each item in the list,
and then return a new list with only the items that passed your Boolean operator,
passed that filter's test.
So let's say that I have a list of numbers, like we have 1 to 10,
but I want to filter out any odd numbers.
How would I do that?
Well, there is another block that helps you with that type of filtering.
It's keep items from a list that pass a certain Boolean test.
So you see that it's structurally similar to the map block.
So here, I can take that same list of numbers, I can duplicate it.
Oops, didn't mean to click on it.
Let's duplicate it, drop it here.
Okay, now what do I put in that ring to filter the list?
I need to think about how I would identify what is even and what's odd.
So I would use the mod operator for that, and a Boolean equals.
So here, I would say, okay, anything that's divisible by 2 without remainder is even.
We can just test that by putting in 2, and you see that that's true,
but if I put in 3, that's false.
So in the same way that we left a slot open in the map block,
for the map block to apply to each item of the list,
we'll do the same thing here with this block.
We're going to drop it into the ring, and then I'm going to say,
keep items such that they pass this test, and then apply it to our list.
So if we try this, you see that we get back, in fact, a list that's now been filtered.
All the odd numbers have been filtered out,
and we get a list that only contains the even numbers,
that's half the length of our original list.
Great, but there's one more thing that we can do with these blocks
that's really kind of fascinating.
We can also take a list and perform an operation
that combines all the elements together.
Now, you might say, like, why would you want to do that?
Well, imagine that you're trying to create a sum, for example.
So we've got items 1 through 10, but you might want to say,
okay, what's the sum of those items?
So if I wanted to add up 1 through 10, what would the total be?
So again, we can use the plus here to do that,
but here you have to think about, we're going to take 1,
and then we're going to add it to the next item in the list, 2,
and then we want to take 1 plus 2, 3, and add it to the next item in the list, 3,
and so on and so forth.
So we're actually kind of working with two slots here,
because as we go through the list, we want to have what's been accumulated
in terms of what's been calculated already,
and we want to have the new item in the list
that we want to add to that accumulating number.
So in order to perform an operation that combines everything,
we need to leave these two slots open in our operator.
And so here we will take, as I've already hinted, combine,
and it's got a similar format, although it puts the ring at the end.
And so we'll take the numbers 1 through 10,
and we're just going to take this plus,
and here we just leave both slots open.
And kind of incredibly, when you click on this, you get the answer,
that if you add up 1 through 10, all the numbers in that list,
you get the result 55.
So with these three tools in your toolbox,
you can process lists very quickly and very efficiently.
They're also, of course, combinable.
So if you want to apply a map to something,
maybe double the numbers, and then combine them to get a result,
you can do that.
We'll take our numbers 1 through 10 here,
we'll double everything, and then we'll combine it.
So here you can see that, in fact, it is double of what we had previously,
110, rather than 55.
There's lots of really creative ways that you can apply
these three blocks in combination.
And as we go forward in our course, we'll look at some of those,
particularly as we get results back from our calls out to network services
that may provide lists of lists, and we need to abstract from those lists,
gather information, and to turn them into new lists
that we can then use in our programs.
So thank you for joining me.
I hope that you'll try these blocks out,
and I'll see you in the next video.