Hi, everyone.
Welcome back to Programming for a Networked World.
Today, we're going to continue our exploration
of textual analysis in NetSplox.
In particular, what we're going to do today
is to explore frequency analysis.
Frequency analysis looks at the appearance
of letters in documents and uses that
to tell certain things about the documents
that you wouldn't otherwise know.
It's often a technique used in cryptography to break codes.
But today, we're going to be using it
for a different purpose.
We're going to try to see if we can identify
the language of a document without looking
at the document itself, just by looking at the frequency
at which certain letters appear.
All right, are you ready to explore
the world of international literature in NetSplox?
Let's get started.
So to do our program, we're going to have
to draw on several sources today.
One is we're going to need a list of the frequency of letters
in various languages.
And then we're going to need to connect to a source that
will allow us to bring down documents.
And then we'll have to turn those documents into letters,
count how frequently they appear,
and then compare the two sources together,
the list of how letters appear in languages in general,
and then how they appear in this document in particular.
And that will tell us, hopefully,
what language the document was written in.
So let's get started by just pulling in our data sources.
So I will go over here.
And I've got up on GitHub a list of data
showing the frequency in which letters
appear in various languages.
So you can see in the English language,
the letter A appears 8% of the time, 7% in French, 6%
in German, 11% in Spanish, and so on and so forth.
So that will tell us, in general,
what we should expect to see when
we're looking at a document in terms of how frequently
a letter appears or ought to appear in that document.
Of course, it all depends on the length of the document
and what the document's about.
If you have Winnie the Pooh, for example,
you might have a lot more W's and a lot more O's,
just because Winnie and Pooh are mentioned a lot.
So in this particular case, we wouldn't
know if it would match exactly with our expectation of W,
which appears only 2% of the time in English.
But it might appear more in that particular volume.
So the actual percentages will vary
depending on what volume we choose to analyze.
But we can expect that, roughly, they
will correspond to these percentages that we see here.
So let's get these first into Nets Blocks.
So the way to do that, we're going to look at this.
We'll turn it into the raw view, which just makes a nice CSV.
And we'll grab that URL.
And I'm going to go over to Nets Blocks.
And I'm going to go to the sensing block.
And let me bring over this URL here.
And then I'm going to drop that particular link in here.
And you see that we get back a text block showing that link.
So that's good so far.
But it's not a CSV.
But fortunately, there is a tool for that here
under Operators, Split.
And we can put this up here.
And I can drop the URL inside it.
There we go.
And the amazing thing about Split,
I'll just move Ada over a little bit,
because it's a really long URL.
Oh, let me zoom in a little bit better
so we can see this all.
Well, I guess I'll leave it at this zoom.
So you can see that it's a CSV here.
And we have a chance to split by something.
Let's see.
But I'm not seeing the by, which I keep moving.
Let's just pull it out here.
Well, there we go.
So here's the by.
I'm going to set it first.
You can set it to split by CSV, comma separated values.
So let me drop that in here again.
Now we've got the by CSV at the bottom.
That's good.
If I click on that, you see now that we
have this list of list formats.
So that was actually pretty easy to bring
this data into Nets Blocks.
OK.
So then our next step is we hit Escape here and get back out.
There we go.
Our next step, then, is to assign that to a variable.
Let's make a variable.
And let's call it letter frequency.
So I will go under Variables here, make a variable,
call it letter frequencies.
OK.
And we don't need to see it on the stage.
Let's bring it over.
And we'll set letter frequencies to this.
All right, so now we've got our letter frequencies.
So that's great.
The next step we want to do is to think
about where we'll actually get the volume that
we'll be analyzing.
So in this case, there's a site called Project Gutenberg.
There we go.
And if you see Project Gutenberg here,
we can just look at popular books.
There are all kinds of books that are freely available.
And so it'd be great to analyze one of these.
Now, there's fortunately a built-in RPC to Project
Gutenberg inside of Netsblocks.
So let's go over to Netsblocks again.
And let's look at our list of RPCs.
And I'll bring this over here.
And you can see here that under Text, I believe,
let's see our Language, we've got Project Gutenberg.
And so let's drop down.
And there's several things we can do here.
We can search, we can get info, and we can get text.
So we might want to search for a book.
Let's do a title.
And let's say, I said Winnie the Pooh.
So let's search for that, see if they're there.
There are a couple books now that have Winnie in the title.
We don't know what they are until we actually look at them.
So let's grab 34551.
And I can go to this now to get the info of 34551
and call that.
And this is which Winnie?
Don't know much about that, but we
can go with that one for now.
OK.
So that's how we get information about a book.
And if we actually want to get the book itself,
let me just duplicate this.
We just switch this now to get the text.
I'll have to enter that again, 34551.
And we click on that, and there's the full text.
OK, so that's great.
Now comes the interesting part.
How do we look at the frequency of the letters
inside of Project Gutenberg?
So this is where we're going to need to think about how
to bring this text into Nextbox.
Then we're going to split it apart by letter.
Then we're going to look at the letter frequencies
and then we'll report back that information
in the form of a list.
OK, so we'll need to make a block for that.
I think it's better to do that inside of a block.
So we're going to make a block.
We'll have it be a reporter.
We're going to call it, let's see, letter frequency.
OK, and let's make it an operator.
There we go.
And we'll do that.
OK, we'll add here an input called text.
And let's make that input text type.
Say OK.
There we go.
So now we can work with this.
And the question is, how do we build this block?
Well, let's assume that what's passed in
is the text of the document.
So we'll start from there.
And the first thing that we want to do
is get that document and split it by its letters.
So let's make another variable.
We'll start using some script variables here.
So let's go over to variables and let's
get the script variable.
And let's call this one just letters, OK?
So now let's set letters to.
Now here's what we need to think about.
We want to set letters to this document
but split into its individual letters.
So we're going to go back to that split operator
we used before and bring it over.
Here we go.
And this time we're going to split the text,
but not by CSV, but by letter.
OK, so now we should have all of the letters in the document.
But our goal is to get the frequency in which
those letters appear.
So let's make another variable for this called frequencies,
or just frequency.
There we go.
And that's supposed to be a list.
So let's start off by just making sure
that we set it as a list because, as we know,
that's a common source of error not setting
the variable correctly.
So let's say frequency here.
And we're just going to set it to an empty list for now.
So that'll be what we want to fill up with our analysis here.
So then the next part of what we need to do
is to think about how to start calculating those frequencies.
Well, we want a list of A to Z. So we
need to look for each letter A to Z, which
means that we need to say, let's loop from A until the letter
Z and then look for their occurrence.
In order to make a loop like that,
we need to get a list of letters from A to Z.
So we could just list it out, just put a list together
and just start filling in like A and then B and then C.
I don't really want to do that because most programmers
are lazy and they like to find easier, shorter ways
to do things.
So let's do a little trick to do this.
So we're going to make another variable here called letters.
And then I will bring over the set block.
And we'll set letters.
But what will we set it to?
Now, here's the trick.
We can use Unicode for this purpose.
And so I will bring over a map block.
And I'm going to go to this operator here called,
let's see, from, is it here?
Yeah, OK, so we want Unicode of as a number.
So we're going to map these numbers.
We're going to map a list of numbers.
And we're going to turn each of those numbers, which
are the Unicode equivalent of our alphanumeric characters
into the character itself and build a list that way.
So we just need over what.
And here's where we would go to a list.
And we'll just create numbers from, not from 1 to 10,
but from the portion of Unicode in which these lowercase
letters appear.
That happens to be just off the top of my head.
No, I've got it written down, 97 to 122.
So that now will take 97 to 122 and then convert those
from numbers into the alphanumeric equivalent
according to the Unicode chart.
And that means that we'll just develop our letters
without actually having to write it all out,
which saves us time and is a more fun way to do it anyway.
So then the next thing that we need to do is,
if I can get this to pull down a little bit more.
There we go.
We want to do a for each loop.
So we're going to take each letter,
and we're going to iterate over it.
So let's go over here to variables.
We're already there.
Grab this for each.
Drop it in here.
We're going to change this now to letter.
And for each letter in our list of letters,
so that's going to be from A to Z. So it'll be A, and then B,
and then C, and then D, and so forth.
We'll do something.
So how do we do this?
Well, we want to look for every occurrence of the letter
in the particular document.
And these are really big documents,
so these are really long lists of letters.
So we'll take a kind of approach that
shrinks our list each time so that at each successive pass,
our list is smaller.
And we're doing that for performance reasons.
So the way that we'll calculate it is,
we'll take the starting length of the list,
and then we'll subtract all the letters
that we're looking for in that list, so like all the A's.
And then we'll see what the ending length of that list is.
And based on the difference between the starting
length and the ending length, we'll
know how many times a particular letter appeared in that list.
But at the same time, we'll also be shrinking our list
so that we'll be making the list smaller.
So to do that, we need to set up some more script variables.
But now, inside of this particular loop here,
so we're going to do this.
We'll say starting length, and then we'll
make another one that's ending length.
And so with starting length and ending length,
we'll have the information we need
to do that kind of calculation.
So we'll begin by setting the starting length here
under variables, set the starting length.
And what will we set it to?
We'll set it to the, oh, actually, this probably,
we've got letters in there twice.
So that's a mistake.
Let's change this one here to document.
And we'll just change this one here down to document.
There, OK, that's clear.
So we're going to start this with setting
the length to the document, the whole document, all
the letters.
And then we'll use this higher order function here
called keep.
And what keep does is just allows
us to keep the information in the list that we want
and get rid of everything else.
So let's bring this over, keep.
And we'll set the document.
So this is going to mutate the list to what we actually keep.
So here we'll go set, drop it in here.
We're going to set document there to what we keep.
And so this requires an input, and that input
is going to be document.
And then we'll set the document to what we actually keep.
And then what we keep, well, you might
think we're going to keep the letter.
But actually, we want to keep every letter except
for the letter that we're looking for.
So let's bring over a not here, put it in here.
And then the question is, what are we not keeping?
We're not keeping the letter in the document
that this is equal to.
So we'll leave this slot open, and we'll
say, if this letter is equal to that letter,
if it's not equal to that letter now,
then we'll keep that item in the list.
But anything that is equal to that letter
will be filtered out.
And so now, at the end of this, we
need to take our length of the list of letters
that's in document after our second pass.
So that's the ending length.
And copy that.
Let's see, we'll just bring it down from here.
OK?
And now, we need to just have some kind of way
to collect this.
So I think we've got our frequency list here,
and we'll add that information to the frequency list.
So let's go to our list here of add.
OK?
Drop that in here.
And what we want to add now is the difference
between the starting length and the ending length.
OK.
And we're going to add that to frequency.
And then, at the end of all this,
we simply just want to report the frequency.
So that's what comes out of this particular block,
this function.
So let's go to Control.
And we'll report this one down here.
OK.
And I'm going to report frequency.
I can drag it down there.
There we go.
OK.
That should be what we want.
Now, here's the test of it.
Let's see if it actually works.
We'll bring it over.
Here's our letter of frequency.
Let's just do it with a simple, like, this is a test.
We won't do anything complicated there.
All right, so this is not quite what I expected.
Let's see what's going on here.
All right.
So we're splitting the document by the letter.
We're turning frequencies to a list.
We're mapping Unicode over numbers 97 to 92.
For each letter and letter, we're
getting the start and ending count.
Oh, oh, oh.
Here's our mistake right here.
We need to change this to length of,
because we're counting the number of letters
in this document, not actually adding the document itself.
So let's do that.
There we go.
And then we can do the same thing if we just duplicate.
Oops.
Duplicate that one down here.
There we go.
All right.
Let's try it again.
OK.
Yeah.
So now it's working.
We've got a list that goes from 1 to 26.
So each one of those is from A to Z.
And then here is the count of those numbers
per their frequency in the document.
So let's try to run this over a real text.
So here we go.
Let's bring this text over.
We're going to get the whole text there.
And we'll count the letter frequencies.
So it'll go out to Project Gutenberg,
get that particular text.
And then we'll do this count and see what it gives us.
Takes us a little while because it's
doing quite a few operations.
So we'll see.
There we go.
OK.
So quite a few As.
It's a big book.
So here are distributions of the letters
in this particular document.
Now, what we want to do then is to think
about the percentages of these letters as they appear.
Because that's how we're going to be able to compare them,
not just based on the actual absolute numbers,
but the percentages in which they appear in that document.
So let's assign these two variables.
So up here, we'll go to Set.
And I'm going to just put on some script variables here.
Let's see.
So we'll set book here.
And then we'll set the book down here
to the actual Project Gutenberg book that we grabbed.
And then we will set the, let's make another variable here.
That would be, say, book frequency, book letter
frequency.
And we'll set book letter frequency to this.
We'll drop the book into here.
OK, so far, so good.
And now we want to set the percentage of appearance
of letters, of letter frequency, just
to differentiate between the absolute frequency
and the percentage in which those letters appear.
So we'll do this.
And now let's take this letter frequency.
OK, how do we convert that?
So let's get the absolute count, so count of letters.
And we can get the absolute count,
because we've already converted this.
This is the text here.
So we just need to convert those into letters themselves.
So we've done that inside of our function.
So it's maybe a little redundant.
But let's just do it here again.
So we'll set count of letters.
And we'll do the length.
Let's see here.
The length of the split into letters
of the book split by letter.
OK, so that should give us that amount.
And now, percentage of the letter frequencies.
This is where we need to use a map,
because we want to take that number of the absolute count.
And for each one of our counts, we
want to divide it by that number.
So let's do this.
Let's go to letter sum.
And we're going to map here.
Let's take a look here.
We're going to map.
And what we're going to map is each one of those entries
divided by the count of letters.
And what we're mapping over is our book letter frequency.
But now, as I told you, we actually
want to then turn these into percentages that
are out of 100.
So in order to do that, we're going to multiply here
the operator discount by 100.
Let's put it in here.
And that will make it comparable with our other list.
OK, so let's try that.
And let's see how we go here.
Let's report something here.
So let's report under Control.
We'll report percentage letter frequency.
Let's do that.
OK, this may take a while to run, but let's see how it goes.
So as you see here, we're going out and calculating
this letter frequency.
We're not using that yet, but it's still
part of our stack that we're building up.
Then we're getting the particular book.
We are getting the letter frequencies for that book.
And now we get the percentages.
So here, you can see that here are the total percentages.
And if you added these up, you would get to 100.
OK, so now we have what we need to compare.
We actually now have two lists.
We've got a list of the actual percentages
of these letters' appearances in a book.
And then beyond that, we have the list
of what we expect to see out of the entire English language
for the frequency of letters as they appear
over all of English literature.
And we want to compare the two.
And by comparing them, we'll see if this book
was written in English.
This one, I think we probably already
know is written in English.
But we'll try some others that aren't.
So I'm going to pause here for today.
I think that's enough for one video.
And what we'll do in our next video
is we'll learn how to plot these results,
compare them with each other, and then
be able to determine using those plots whether a book is
written in a particular language.
So we'll come back to that next week.
But thank you very much for joining me this week
and talk to you again soon.