Hi everyone, welcome back to our series on programming for a networked world.
In this video, we're going to the movies. Well, to the movie database at least. Our project is
going to query this online database to find films with particular words in the titles.
We'll then loop through the results, writing the titles on the stage. Do you know how many
treatments of Frankenstein there are? After this nifty exercise, you will. This exercise combines
a number of programming concepts that we first met in other videos, including for loops, lists,
and variables. You'll see how we can combine these elements to create a sophisticated program,
and you'll also get a sneak peek at Netbox's ability to connect with data sources across
the internet. All right, ready to channel your inner film critic? Let's get started.
Okay, so we're going to retrieve movie titles and list them on the stage. We're going to build
this program block by block, and I want to explain the thought process as we move along,
but I want to talk a little bit about the call block from the red category before we begin.
So let's take a look at that block now. Here I'll bring it over, and it's under the network tab.
Here we go. Call. Okay. This call block with its companion run block allows Netbox to make remote
procedure calls. That is, these two blocks allow you to connect with other systems and perform
some prescribed action. For instance, we're going to use the call block to connect with the
movie database API. The term API is short for Application Programming Interface. An API provides
the rulebook for interacting with another system. In Netbox, we use this call block to make remote
procedure calls to application programming interfaces. These calls allow us, among other
things, to request and retrieve information that we would not have otherwise in our program.
In this case, for instance, we're going to use the call block to search for movie titles
matching a given keyword, and then to display those titles in a list. To do this, we need to
use the drop-down menus to navigate to MovieDB, and then we're going to use the drop-down menu
to select the precise API that we want to call. So let's see over here. When we do that, we've got a
long list, and we want to go to MovieDB, and then we're going to select Search Movie, and you'll see
that now it's asking for a string title. Okay, let's add the term Frankenstein.
So go over here, put in Frankenstein, and what will happen when we click it?
We get back a list of numbers. So what do these numbers represent? Well, we can right-click here
and click Help, and we see that for the MovieDB database and the Search Movie operation,
that it searches for a given movie and returns movie IDs. So you can search for a title of a movie.
It will return to the title of that movie in the MovieDB database. The IDs themselves do not have
intrinsic meaning. To get to the titles of the movies to which they correspond, we need to make
a call to the MovieDB database again. So let's try that. We're going to take one of these numbers,
and then we're going to send it back to the MovieDB database to get the actual title of the
movie with that ID in the database. So let's try it with title 3, let's say 3103. So 3103, we call
that, and oh, we need to change this now to Movies, and we want to get the title of the movie. So we'll
move down here, and now it says, okay, ID 3103. Click on that. So that ID corresponds to the title
House of Frankenstein in the MovieDB database. So if you're counting, you see that we have to make
two calls to get the title. First, we query for the movie ID, and then we send the movie ID back
to get the title of the movie that matches that ID. So if we want to search for, say, 20 movies,
we need to make 21 calls in all. First, we get a list of 20 items, and those are the 20 IDs that
we're going to use, and then we need to iterate through that list, and we're going to use a
for loop for that to go find each of the titles of those IDs in turn. Not every API works the same
way, of course. Some allow you to pass a list of IDs, or the equivalent, and to receive a list back
so that you can reduce your calls to just two. In general, it's better to minimize your remote
procedure calls to avoid tying up other systems and to make your own program go faster. But in the
grand scheme of things, calling out 21 times to the MovieDB database shouldn't pose any problems.
So we'll be exploring a lot of the remote procedure calls available in NetsBlocks throughout
this course, and the team is adding new remote procedure calls all the time. But let's stop with
these preliminaries, and let's get started with the project itself. We've got our MovieDB search
movie title, and that will be a central block. But we don't want to just ask for Frankenstein,
we want to leave it open so you can ask for any type of movie you like. So let's have the program
ask a question. What movies would you like? Or maybe it should be which, to be more proper, right?
There we go. And then the answer will be contained in this answer. Now, when we make this call out,
remember we're going to want to keep this list in memory. We're going to want to iterate through it
20 times. So I think that we'll create a variable, and let's do that as a script variable. So I'll
put that right here, maybe at the top. And then we're going to set that script variable here
to the result of calling out to the MovieDB database for movies with that particular title.
Oh, and we need to change this to MovieList, say. Okay, so MovieList, and we'll change that then.
Okay, so when this calls out, this should set the variable to MovieList, and then we can
work with the results. All right, the other thing that we want to do then is have this program
right on the stage. So how should we do that? Well, we'll start with clearing the stage,
nothing's written there, and then I think we're going to have under Looks,
we're going to use Hide. Okay, so Hide allows us to hide the sprite so the stage is visible,
even though the sprite will still be able to write on the stage. So let's try that out.
There we go, and there's our question being asked. So, so far, so good. I'll just stop it right there.
Let's keep going. Okay, so now we've hidden Ada, and we're ready to write in the stage,
but how do we write in the stage? Well, under Pen, we can go over here, and there's a
Write on the Stage. Now, the thing is, if we just click on Write in the Stage, hello, size 12,
it'll just put it right in the middle where Ada was standing. We actually want to set the coordinates
so that it writes in the right place, and let's do that by moving it. And so we'll start,
let's say, we'll start by going to a particular point in the stage,
and I think, so the x variable here, we probably want to have it negative 150,
and the y at maybe negative 100. Let's see where that moves us.
I don't know. Okay, so we need to have the y at 150. There we go.
Okay, that looks about the right place to be writing, and so then every time we write,
we want to sort of move down a little bit so that we don't just write on top of our
results as we go along. So let's see how that works. Stop here, and we're going to put the
write in, but now when we're writing this out, we're not writing out the list. We want to write
out each of the titles in turn, and this is where we need a for loop. So let's go over here to
control, and we'll grab our for loop, and we're going to drop it in here. And how, you know,
how many results do we want to iterate through? Well, it depends on how many results came back
from our query initially to the movie database. So we'll go over to the variables, and we're going
to get the length of whatever came back here. So let's go to length of, and we'll say the movie list.
There we go. So we're going to iterate from the first item in that list until the last item in
that list, and then we're going to do something. Namely, we're going to write on the stage,
but we still haven't called out again to get the actual title. So let's put that in,
and we don't need to create a variable necessarily for that. We can just take the call block over,
and we can drop it into right here. Drop this down to movie database.
It's over to movies, and we're going to get the title, and now we just need to pass in
the id from that list. So what id is it? Well, the iterator will tell us.
It's number one, number two, number three, and so on in that list. So now we need to go back to
variables and just get this item one of right here. And so it's not item one of anymore, it's item i.
That's the iterator that we're using. So each time that we iterate, as I said, that will increase by
one automatically, and that will help us to move our way through this list. And so we'll just put
the list here. It's our list of movies, and then we can write it in size 12. And again, the one
thing we need to do is move down a little bit each time so that we're not writing on top of each other.
So let's do that with move, and basically we need to kind of do two things. We want to sort of set
the margin back on the left-hand side, so we'll set x here because x will always be at negative 150.
And then with y, we're going to change y by negative 10. So x will always go back to the
same place, but y will continue to move down the screen as we go. All right, and
I think that's good. Let's give it a nice hat block to get started, so we can start with a click.
There we go. And with any luck, this should work. So what movie should we like to see? Let's say
Frankenstein, and there we go. We get a nice list of movies. Now if you want to be even fancier,
you could take the iterator, for example, and make that an ordered list. Let's take a look here. I
want to go to operators, and I want to join here two things. One is going to be the title. Well,
actually, let's expand this a little bit. You can see that you can expand that block, and I'm going
to pull in this. This will just be a space, and then I'm going to use the iterator here.
And so now, instead of writing hello, I'll have, let's put a period there too. That looks
very formal. We'll have one dot the name, two dot the name, and so forth and so forth.
And let's change the size a little bit, so it's a little bit bigger.
And I've got to make sure I'm spelling it correctly too. Frankenstein.
Okay, so let's review what we learned in this session. We saw how to call out to a data source
on the web using an RPC, and then to pull back data in the form of a list. And then we used a
for loop to iterate through that list one item at a time and print its title on the stage.
So why don't you try this for yourself and share in the comments how it went,
and I'll see you in my next video.