Hi, my name is Cliff Anderson. I'm Associate University Librarian at
Vanderbilt University and a member of Vanderbilt's Computational Thinking and
Learning Initiative. And in this second of our series on Nets Blocks, I'm going
to explore how to draw geometric shapes on the screen. We're going to draw simple
shapes on the stage using so-called command blocks. You're going to learn
about turtle graphics, a novel idea for teaching kids and the young at heart how
to program. And you're also going to learn about the concept of state and
side effects, which we're going to explore in greater depth as we go along.
So, ready to try out your digital drawing techniques? Let's get started.
So, what are turtle graphics? Today is going to be all about drawing. Drawing simple
shapes like squares and triangles on the stage. But before we get started, I'd like
to share a little bit about the way that this graphical approach to computer
programming developed. The idea is called turtle graphics or turtle geometry.
Seymour Papert, a computer science educator who spent the majority of his
career at MIT, developed the concept of turtle graphics in the 1960s. Papert
aspired to create an environment for computational exploration, for learning
by doing, so to speak. Inspired by the educational theories of Jean Piaget,
Papert wanted kids to learn the principles of mathematics, not by
memorizing a bunch of theorems, but by extrapolating rules from the success or
failure of experiments they carry out. He termed this theory constructionism, and
went about creating a software environment to enable those experiments
in learning. The software language he co-developed is called Logo, and a
distinguishing feature of Logo is turtle graphics. This is the humble turtle that
we're talking about. It looks more like an arrowhead than a turtle, but just use
your imagination. The default sprite in Netsblocks is indeed this abstract
turtle, but you can also give the sprite any costume you like. If you want, you can
also make it look like a real turtle. Just come over here and click on this
right here, and you can see costumes, and sometimes it takes a moment to load.
We're waiting. We're still waiting. It's almost there.
Once it loads, you can see here that you've got lots of options to shape your
particular sprite. If you want, you can turn it into a beetle. You can turn
it into a butterfly. Lots of different options, but we're going to stick with,
for now, this so-called simple turtle shape. The turtle moves around the
stage using a Cartesian plane. The tip of the turtle, when it starts, is pointing to
0, 0. So when you create a new program in Netsblocks, you'll always start your
turtle out at 0, 0. Let's try this for ourselves. I'm going to drag this x, y
block over here, go to x, 0, and y, 0, and then let's try clicking on it and see
what happens. If I click on the button, I move back a little bit, but then when I
click again, nothing happened. So why isn't anything happening? Well, when I
click on the block, the sprite doesn't move because it's already at the center
of the stage at coordinate 0, 0. But if we change some of the values in the block
to find the boundaries of the stage, then we'll see that it indeed moves into
different places. So here, if I change the sprite to x, 180, y, 0, you're going to
expect it to move along the x-axis to the right. And if we move back to the
center, we can move, for example, on the y-axis to 180. Oh, it disappeared off the
side of the screen, but top of the screen, but no worries. Let's bring it back to
120. There it is. We can go to negative 120. That's going to drop us below, and
we'll see. If we click on that, there it goes. And of course, you can get to any
coordinate this way just by putting your x and y values. So you see that whenever
we enter a coordinate value on this Cartesian plane, the sprite will move to
that particular place. And using that combination of x and y values, we're able
to move the sprite all around the stage. But when we're drawing figures, this has
its limitations. Just moving the sprite around the stage gets old quickly. If we
want to draw shapes, we don't want to just hop around. That's not really the
best way to do things. There might be a way to do it, but we'll get to that later.
What we need is a couple of other blocks to turn these movements into actual line
drawings. So we're going to select from two categories of blocks in the palette
to make our movements more productive, namely the motion blocks and the pin
blocks. So where do I find those? Here's motion. We're already on it. And then
these green ones are the pin blocks. So the first blocks that we're going to
bring over are two of the motion blocks, move 10 steps and point in direction.
Now you notice that point in direction has here a number already in it. And if you
drop down, you can see that that number, 90 degrees, stands for right. And you can
see that 180 degrees stands for down, and zero degrees stand for up. So it's sort
of like the directions in a compass. And if we combine these with the move block,
then we can start moving the sprite in different directions around the stage
any number of steps. So let's just start back. Well, I'll put this at 0, 0. I'm
going to click on that, and it'll go to 0, 0. And then let's take this and say, okay,
we're going to put that point in direction there. Point in direction 0, so that's
pointing down. And move, let's say, 50 steps. Try that. And sprite's not moving.
Do you know why? We're always going back to point 0, 0, so it doesn't look like
there's any movement. But now we can see that when we disconnect it from going
back to the beginning, the sprite is moving up. All right, let's draw a square
with this. These two blocks provide us with what we need to walk a figure like a
square or a circle. But we want to see some of the product of our sprite's
voyage around the stage. To trace the sprite's steps, we need a different kind
of block. And that's, again, under this pin category. So I'm going to bring over
pin down and pin up. So these two blocks will tell the system to either start
tracing a line on the stage or to stop tracing a line on the stage. And if we
use them in conjunction with the move blocks, we can get the turtle to draw a
figure for us. Let's start simply. We're just going to create a square on the
center of the stage. So, okay, I'm going to place this sprite at the center of the
stage. And then I'm going to take these blocks, which I've already got, and I'm
going to duplicate them four times. You can right-click on it and get these
duplicates. So I'm just going to do that four times. Here we go. Okay. And now we
want to start moving the sprite around. Okay. So I'll put the first one up here
and the second one here. And we want to turn this time to make a square. Let's
start by turning to the right. And then we're going to move this one and we're
going to go down. And this one will go to the left. Let's see how that works.
Well, it did something, but it didn't actually draw anything. So in order to
see this, I'm going to pull down the stack of blocks. You see how they
disconnect? And I'm going to put pen down right here. And I'm going to reattach
them by lifting them up. You see that white line? That indicates that they'll
snap together when I let go. All right. So when I click this now, you see that I
get a nice square. I still have this pen up block. And what's the purpose of that?
Well, the problem is that if we add something else, for example, let's say we
want to draw a square and then move on to draw another figure, but we didn't
want the figures to be attached to one another. If I just go ahead and pull over
another move block, let's say another move 50 here, and I click on the stack
again, you see that the turtle continued moving and tracing the turtle's steps. To
prevent that, I can do the same experiment, but this time bring the pen
up there, and voila. Ah, it didn't make any change. Again, why is that? Well, it just
traced over itself. So we needed something else here called a clear
block at the beginning. And voila. Now when we run it, it made the nice square
and then moved graciously to the side so that we could see the square. So this
introduces something that we call state. When we make changes using these command
blocks, these blocks that have these notches that fit together that have the
square edges, when we use these command blocks, we're changing the state of the
sprite's little world. That is, our blocks have the effect of altering the
program's environment. For reasons that we'll get into later, these command
blocks actually generate what are called side effects, and we're carrying out
computations by clicking on these command blocks, and those computations
create side effects that become visible on the stage. In Net's blocks, these
changes persist unless we close and reopen our project. So after clicking on
a stack of command blocks, we have to remember where we left the state of the
world. If we forget, for example, to put pen up at the end of drawing, then
whenever we move next, the pen will be in the state of being down, and lines will
appear on the stage. So it's a little bit like when you start a project on your
desk, and you take out all your notebooks and pens and paper, and then you finish
your project. Ideally you want to put all that back so that when you start the
next project, you won't have that mess and clutter in front of you. The same
thing applies to programming languages. You want to be aware of the state so
that when you start your next series of computations, something you did in the
previous series of computations doesn't mess up your environment and produce an
unwanted side effect. Okay, let me wrap up then. We covered a lot in this video. We
learned about turtle graphics, we saw how a sprite moves across a coordinate plane,
and we learned how to draw a square. We also learned something about the concept
of state and side effects. So given what you've learned now, can you write a
program that draws a triangle on the stage? Or if that seems too easy to you,
how about a polygon? Try drawing some different figures, and next time we're
going to see how to create a circle. But the challenge with making a circle is we
want to do it without having to reproduce so many command blocks, because
as easy as they are to create, it gets tiresome to have these big series of
blocks. Next time we're going to learn how to shorten those stacks of blocks by
using control structures to keep it simpler and more compact. But that's
enough for today. Thanks for joining me, and see you next time. Goodbye.