Hi, everyone.
Welcome back to Programming for a Network World.
Today, we're going to begin our exploration of peer-to-peer
networking in Nest Blocks.
In particular, we're going to learn to pass a message
from one Nest Blocks program to another.
So what we're going to be building today
is something called Distributed Hello World.
It's very traditional when you're
starting off in programming for the first time
to write a Hello World program, but we're
going to do it in a fun way.
I'm going to turn it over to Brian
to help us get started with some of the core concepts
we need to write this program in Nest Blocks.
All right, Brian, take it away.
All right, thank you, Cliff.
So as Cliff mentioned, we're going
to be writing a simple program where we have one application
running on a single computer that sends a message,
like Hello World, to another computer, which
then can display this message.
So I'm going to get started with this sender.
If we look under this Network tab or category
here in the palette, we can see that there's
this Send Message block.
So this will actually allow us to send a message
over the internet to another computer or a program running
on a different device.
So if we select this first dropdown,
there's this Message option, and this is the type of message
that we're sending.
So we're just using the built-in message type
provided by Nest Blocks, which has a single field, MSG.
Now, we can enter Hello World into this field.
Now, we just need to figure out who we
want to send this message to.
So Nest Blocks introduces this concept
of a room, which is composed of multiple roles, which
are basically individual subprojects
within this larger distributed application.
So in this case, we mentioned we wanted
to have one computer sending this message
to another computer.
So say this first computer is running this sender
application, which then sends the message
to this receiver application in this bigger distributed
program.
So we can rename our current role Sender,
and then this will correspond to that first application, which
just sends this Hello World message.
And then we can add another role, the Receiver role,
which corresponds to the application running
on a different computer that receives this message, namely
on Cliff's computer.
So I'll invite Cliff to this role.
OK, and so you see that Brian's message pops up on my screen,
and it invites me to join his program.
Now, one thing to note is when you say yes to this,
you're actually going to be leaving the program that you're
in and joining Brian's.
So what's on my screen now when I accept will disappear.
There we go, and you can see that Ada is gone.
And now I see that my program is called Receiver
at Distributed Hello World.
And that's because if you look in the room,
you see me down here.
I'm inside of the Receiver role at Brian's invitation.
Now, Brian has already created the block that
is going to send the message.
So I need to create a receiver on my side
under this Receiver role to be able to display
the message that he sends.
There is one trick that you have to keep in mind.
So let's just go ahead and start.
We'll go to Network, and I'm going to pull out this When I
Receive block here.
But then I get another pop-up saying,
edits cannot be made on projects by guests.
So this is just a little bit of insurance.
You can invite someone to join one of your projects
and take a role, but not be allowed
to actually edit the code.
So if we want to edit the code together,
then Brian has to give me permission.
So I'm going to request permission from Brian,
see if he accepts.
QUINN CLIFFE requests permissions,
and I see a dialogue pop up on my screen that
asks if I would like to actually make him a collaborator.
So in other words, elevate his permissions from someone
who cannot just play the game to someone
who can actually edit the application
or the underlying code of the Receiver role in this case.
So now that Brian has done that,
I can bring that block back over,
and you see that now it sticks in the coding area.
So all I have to do then is say, when I receive a message,
that's the name of the message, and then I
get the content of the message here.
And so we'll just need to have, oh, well,
we only have a turtle here.
Let's bring Ada back over.
Remember, we lost her in the transition.
So there is Ada.
And so we want Ada to respond now
when this message comes through.
So this is Steve Wozniak traveling back in time,
sending messages to Ada Lovelace,
but let's see if it works.
So I'm going to then say, and what do I say?
I don't say hello.
What I want to say is the content of that message that
came through for two seconds.
And that should be all that it takes.
So let's see if Brian sends that message,
whether I can receive it.
All right, so if I click this Send Message block,
we'll see that nothing shows up on Cliff's screen.
Because if we look back at our code,
we have this Send Message block, but we never
filled out who the recipient was going to be.
So if we select this dropdown, now we
can see Receiver, because Receiver
is the name of the other role in our room,
as well as a couple other options, like Others in Room
and Everyone in Room.
So we can now select Receiver.
And now when we click the block, we
can see that Ada says, hello, world.
So that's a really quick introduction to these concepts.
We're going to be building on them in future videos.
But now you understand the concept of a room,
roles within room, and how to send
messages between those roles.
So thanks, everybody, and we'll see you in our next video.