Hi, everyone. Welcome back to Programming for a Network World.
Today, we're going to explore the basics of the NetsBlox interface.
Our goal today is to help you to get oriented in NetsBlox,
so that you'll know where all the pieces
are as we continue our programming journey.
We'll explore how to write a simple program in
NetsBlox and look at the different components of
NetsBlox so that you'll know your way around as we go through this course.
Are you ready to find out how to program in NetsBlox? Let's get started.
Let's begin with just how to get to NetsBlox.
If you type NetsBlox into a browser,
www.netsblocks.org, you'll get to this page.
To get to the NetsBlox programming environment,
you can click Try Now.
That URL is editor.netsblocks.org.
That will bring you to this page where we'll do all of our programming.
Now, one of the things that you'll want to do is to
create your own account in NetsBlox.
An account allows you to keep your programs in one place,
they'll keep them private to you,
but you can also share out your programs with others.
To do that, we'll click here on this Cloud icon,
and you can see that I'm already logged in.
But if I were logged out,
I would have another option here,
and that is to sign up.
You can sign up here,
just put in this information,
and then click OK.
You'll have to agree to the terms of service,
and then you can log in with your username and password,
just like any normal site.
Let's try it again. There we go.
Now, I'm logged in under my name.
That's the first thing that you want to do is to create an account on
NetsBlox as you go through this course
to keep all of your exercises in one place.
Now, let's just talk about
the various parts of the NetsBlox interface.
Up here, we have the toolbar that we've already used,
and there are several important features up
there that we'll get to in a little while.
Then over here, we have the palette.
This is where you have the three main types
of blocks that we're going to be using,
namely command blocks.
Those have this notch right here.
Then reporter blocks, for example,
they have the rounded edges like these.
These are reporter blocks.
Reporter blocks differ from command blocks because
command blocks do things in the NetsBlox environment,
whereas reporter blocks report things about the environment.
That distinction will become clear as we go forward in this course.
The third type of block here is with this pointy arrows.
This is a special type of reporter called a Boolean,
and it always reports true or false.
Again, we'll learn more about Booleans
later in this particular unit.
These are your blocks,
and that will be the functionality that we'll use.
What we'll do is we're going to pull these blocks
out onto the scripting area.
This is what this is right here.
This is where we do our scripting or write our programs.
You can see we'll just create a simple program.
We're going to go to the Network tab here,
and I'm going to bring out this call block.
You can see because it has the rounded edges that it is a reporter.
I'll drop down and you'll see
that there's lots of different choices here.
Now, these are what are called RPCs, Remote Procedure Calls.
That is, they can get data from all over
the web and bring it back to your NetBlocks program.
We're going to be exploring RPCs in depth in this course
because it's one of the themes of programming in a network world.
But you may see as we go on that this menu
changes over the period of the course,
and it may actually change in your own environment.
That's simply because we're adding new RPCs all the time,
and sometimes we reorganize them to
just collect them and make them a little bit more clear.
I'm going to go down to GeoData and to weather and click on that,
and you'll see that now I've got this RPC.
It's a little bit different. It has a dropdown here.
I want to drop that down and you see that I've got several options.
I could get, for example,
the humidity, I can get icons representing the weather in a particular area.
What I want to do is get the temperature.
Now, two more spaces for blocks open up.
This is really one of the ways that you'll program in Nest Blocks.
When you have these particular spaces to fill in blocks,
then you'll look for other blocks that you want to use to fill them.
Now, in this particular one,
to get the temperature of where I'm located,
I want the latitude and longitude.
I can look that up in some service,
and it would tell me maybe on
Google Maps what my latitude and longitude is.
But I can also go over to sensing,
and I can find a block over here called my latitude and my longitude.
Again, I can bring these into the scripting area just like so,
and I can then bring them right into these slots.
Make sure you drop it in the right slot like that.
To test this, I simply click on it,
and you see here that there's a pop-up saying
that the editor wants to know my location.
Now again, in order for this to work,
you have to allow that,
and I've got that turned off in the Mac,
so let's make sure it's turned on,
and I'm going to go to location settings here.
This is Mac specific,
but let's get this done for this browser,
and let's see if I can do that.
There we go. That should have it done,
and let's try it again.
This time, it came back with 67.9 degrees Fahrenheit.
We are using Fahrenheit in this particular service.
You see that you may have some setup to do in your own browser simply to allow
the browser to fetch that information for you based on your location,
and that can differ between browsers.
But in any case, once you have that setup in Nest Blocks,
it will always return the temperature that it is right now,
67.9 where I am, it's a nice day.
Now, let's build a little program around that,
and I'll introduce as we build a program
to other parts of the Nest Block programming environment.
The first is the stage.
This is where in some sense your programs will show their results.
The stage is an important area where you can draw,
you can have what are called sprites or turtles,
and the stage is in some sense where the action happens in your program.
You can see here I've got this default little arrow, that's a turtle.
We'll learn about turtle graphics coming up in a little bit.
But this is also something important.
This is your sprite corral.
This is where your sprites for your program will be contained.
Now, sprites are how you organize your programs.
This code, for example, is inside of a particular sprite,
this sprite right here.
If I click on the stage, you'll see that the scripting area becomes blank,
and that's because I can also write programs that are specific to the stage.
But we're going to be writing here in this sprite,
and you may have many sprites,
and they may contain different types of code.
So you'll need to know where you're writing your code
and what sprite is going to be responding to the commands
that you use inside of your code.
So here, we'll just use this particular sprite.
That's the default sprite that looks like the arrow,
and you can see that it will respond,
but we need to use something other than a reporter to do that.
So this is just reporting this information.
This is why there's that pop-up.
But in order for the sprite to do something,
we need to use the command block.
And so the simplest command we can use is let's go under looks here,
and I'm going to take this C block out,
and let's drop this whole thing into say.
Now, what I can do is click on this,
and you'll see that it will fetch the information,
and then it will have the sprite say 67.9 degrees.
But of course, that number is not very helpful or informative.
So let's make this program a little more interesting.
So if we go over to operators, we can go down to this join block,
and this helps join two pieces of text together.
In computer science, text is often called string,
so it will join strings together.
And we can take this particular block and drop it in here,
and we can say the temperature is now,
and I'll put a space after that.
And actually, I can click this little arrow
and then put another space and say Fahrenheit like that.
Let's pull this back so you can see the whole thing.
Now, I've got a string here that will say the temperature is now,
and then 67.9 degrees or whatever the temperature is where you are,
Fahrenheit to make sure that we're not talking about Celsius.
And if I click on that, it will report that information to me
in the form now of a sentence.
So you can see it's much more readable.
And then I can bring this back into that slot here,
and now I can have the sprite say that sentence for two seconds.
If I wanted to stay on the screen a little bit longer,
I could change that to five seconds.
And there you go.
Now, one last thing as we explore the utility in Nest Blocks,
I'm going to bring out this when green flag clicked.
This is called a hat block,
and the hat block can sit on top of the stacks of blocks that you build,
and then you can activate it by hitting this green flag.
Oftentimes, people have a hat block in their program
because it's the way that they kick off the computation of their program
rather than just directly clicking on a stack of blocks.
So let's try that.
I'm going to click green.
You see that the highlight is around it.
There's a little bit of glow around it.
And then the command makes the sprite say that information on the stage,
and then it no longer is glowing.
That means the computation is over.
All right, so there's a lot more to learn about Nest Blocks,
but the purpose here was just to show you how to write a very simple program
as we explore the different parts of the Nest Blocks programming environment.
I hope you've enjoyed this video,
and I look forward to seeing you in the next episode.