Welcome back, everyone, to Programming for a Network
World.
Today, we're going to be continuing
our exploration of peer-to-peer networking within Netsblocks.
So we're going to take this a step further,
and we're going to take a graphic that we're
going to animate on our Netsblocks screen,
and then we're going to have that continue
to animate on another screen.
That is, to move from one program to another,
but have the kind of illusion of the continuity
of that animation.
So you could think about that technique
if you wanted to build a distributed video game
in some way, maybe even like a Pong game that has players
playing on different sides, and then
the Net is where your animation crosses over
to the other person's program.
But for today, we're just going to do the animation part.
And so to get started, let me turn
to Brian, who's joining me again,
and he'll help us get the animation going.
Well, hello, everyone.
Thank you, Cliff.
So as Cliff said, we're going to be
having this animation running from one computer
across the internet to the other computer.
So specifically, we're going to have
a dog that's running across my computer,
and then onto Cliff's, and then back to mine,
and so on and so forth.
So before we get into the networking portion of it,
let's first just try to break this problem down
into how can we animate this dog?
How can we get it to actually appear to be running?
So if we jump into our project right here,
we can see I'm starting from a starter template
where we already have a bunch of different costumes
which show each different, I guess, frame in this animation.
So if we want to show this illusion of running,
all we need to do is change to the next costume
that we have.
We can see that if I click this really quickly,
we get this kind of slow motion, and then we
get this kind of run in slow motion.
So instead of, of course, clicking a bunch of times,
if we want to do something over and over,
we might want to put it in a loop
so I can get this forever loop.
And now we can see that this animates way too fast.
So we can certainly slow this down
to something more reasonable by adding this weight block.
And now we can see that we have this animation of this dog
running at a reasonable speed.
So it's running, but it's running in place.
So we might want to certainly have this dog actually
move as it's running as well.
So we can drop this move 10 steps block into our loop.
Now we can see that the dog runs clear off the screen.
OK, so now we have this, the beginning of this program.
We were able to show this or animate this dog's running
across our screen.
But we certainly probably wanted to make
a couple of additional tweaks.
For example, when the program starts,
we probably want to start at the beginning of the stage.
And then it would probably be nice to know
when it runs off of the screen.
So let's start by looking at how we
might be able to get the program to animate
the dog running from the beginning of the screen
when the green flag is clicked.
So use this one green flag click block.
And then when the green flag is clicked,
we want to move it to the beginning of the screen.
So let's go to, say, 0, 0.
And that's not really where we want the dog to be.
We probably want it in the bottom left corner here.
So we can try something, say, maybe negative 150 for x.
Let's maybe make that negative 175.
Now I can see we're right at the beginning.
Negative 150 for y.
This looks like it's about right.
We've got the dog in the bottom left corner.
And now we probably want to start
at the beginning of the animation.
So we can switch to costume dog 1.
So now we started from the beginning of the animation.
And then we can just broadcast some sort of event.
Actually, let's not worry about the broadcast just yet.
Then we can actually just have the animation start.
So now if we click green flag clicked,
we can see the dog starts in the lower left
and runs across the screen.
So it's looking pretty good.
Now we just need to figure out how
to tell when the dog is off the screen.
And then Cliff can jump right into the networking portion.
So if we're going to run until we're off the screen,
we probably want to make a new variable that keeps track of if
we are still on the screen.
This variable should start with a value of true.
And then when we are doing our whole animation portion,
we want to probably only repeat that
until we're off the screen.
So repeat that until we are actually
no longer on the screen or not on screen.
All right.
Now we throw out a forever loop because we're not
going to be doing this indefinitely anymore.
And to make this a little simpler,
I always want to get into the networking portion
since we're also going to need this animation.
But let's put this script out on its own
and actually broadcast an animate event.
So now when I receive this animate event,
we'll just do the animation while we're on the screen.
And let's give this a try.
If you press the green flag, we can
see we're animating, animating, animating.
But we're off the screen now, and our onScreen value
is still true.
And the problem is that there's no point in this loop
where we're checking to see if we're still on the screen.
So now we just need to add one more block or one more bit
here where we're setting this onScreen variable
to some expression that determines if we're still
on the screen.
So let's see.
We know that our x position is going to be
the important value here.
So we can actually just try to figure out
what the value of x is when we're off the screen
by just running it and just trying to stop it right
when we get off the screen.
There we go.
Let's say 305.
So this is a little bit simplistic.
And there are certainly other ways to do this.
But for now, I think this is sufficient.
So we're just going to check to see if this x position value is
greater than, let's say, 305.
All right, so now when we, whoops.
So this is actually, so you can see I actually did the opposite.
So I was determining how to tell if you're off the screen,
but this variable is whether or not you're on the screen.
So we want to just change this to a not.
We also could just change the sign on the inequality.
All right, so now we see we run off the screen.
And as soon as we're off the screen, onScreen is now false.
All right, so now up until this point,
we've been able to create a running dog where
we animate this running dog moving across our screen.
And we know as soon as it gets off the screen.
Now, once it's off the screen, we're
going to need to have it show up on someone else's computer
and then run across that screen as well.
So I'm going to go to the room and duplicate my role
and name this one Role2 so that when Cliff joins the role,
he'll have the same set of costumes.
So he has everything needed to animate this running dog,
including the scripts that we've made up until this point.
Now, I'm going to invite Cliff and turn it over to him
to finish the networking portion.
All right, thanks, Brian.
So you see I get Brian's invitation.
So I will accept that.
And then, as Brian said, there's his project.
So I get that on my screen, which is fantastic.
You can just double check to see which room I'm in.
I'm in Role2.
I'm in the room, and I'm in Role2 here.
So that's good.
And the only thing is, remember before,
I need to get permission from him
to be able to change his project.
So I'll request permission from Brian.
And now that he's granted that to me,
I can start coding on my side.
So what I need to do then is, as we've seen,
the dog will be running across the screen.
And then when it hits the edge, it stops.
And that's the end of the program so far.
So in order to flip back and let the dog continue
running on Brian's end when it's off the screen on my end,
I need to send a message to Brian.
So I need to use this send message block.
Now, we want to send the message as soon as that block has
turned to that we're at not here.
So let's see.
When we receive, we're going to repeat
until it's not on screen.
So this is setting that as not on screen.
So then after that loop ends is the place I want to put it.
Now, the question is, what do I want to send?
So there is a built-in message.
But we can actually customize your messages.
And this is important because you
may be sending various types of messages back and forth.
And they may actually contain different types of data payload.
And so here, we're going to customize and create
our own message.
The thing is, when you're building a distributed program
like this, it's really crucial that you
know what the type of message is that you're sending.
Because if I just send him any message with any name
and Brian doesn't know what that name is,
he won't be able to know what to receive.
So let's just create here a make a message type.
And the name of the message is going to be,
let's call it Enter Dog.
And the field will be, now, what should the field be?
What kind of information am I trying to pass back?
Well, again, to preserve the continuity of the animation,
we actually want to know where the dog is
in terms of its gait.
Like, what is it doing when it's running?
Are its legs together or its legs apart?
And in order to know that, we actually
just want to pass back the number of the costume
that we're using.
So the costumes all have these numbers here.
And even if they weren't numbered themselves,
there are a numbered sequence here.
So basically, what we want to say
is whatever costume number we're on
is what we're going to pass back.
So I'm going to say I'll call this field Costume Number,
just so that's clear.
And so now I have that available to me.
And if I drop down here, I can say Enter Dog.
And you can see that it says Costume Number.
Now, the costume number I can get under Sensing.
And here it says Costume Number of.
And I want to drop down to not the stage, but the dog.
And if I click on that, it'll tell me
that it's right now in 4.
But we're not going to hard code that, of course.
We're just going to drop that in.
Let me make sure I get enough space for you all to see that.
OK.
So that's going to be, oh, wrong slot.
There we go.
And then I need to send this to role 1.
So the message will go back to the role that Brian's in,
but containing the information that Brian
needs to keep that animation smoothly running.
Now, the other thing is, when I receive a message back
from Brian, I'm going to need to also handle that on my end.
Otherwise, it would just be like,
as soon as it runs off my screen,
it would never come back.
And so we'll go to Network here.
And we're going to take When I Receive.
And I'm going to drop this down.
And I'm going to get that same message.
So whenever I receive an Enter Dog,
then I need to handle that with some animation on my end.
Now, remember, I'm getting this message
when the dog has run off the side of Brian's screen.
So it should make an entrance on the left hand of my screen
as it continues to run across.
We actually already know where that is.
If we just duplicate this block up here and I pull this down,
that's the starting point.
It's already in there.
Now, the thing is, switch to costume Dog 1.
That's where we need to say, no, it's actually not Dog 1.
It's the costume number that comes through
when we receive that message.
So we'll replace that.
We want to set onScreen to true.
And then we're going to broadcast back to animate.
And that will do the animation running all the way
through until it reaches the end and it's not on screen anymore.
And then we send the message to Brian
to continue the animation on his end.
Brian, I think we've got all the pieces in place.
What do you think?
I think so.
Let's give it a try.
All right, now let me bring my screen
and make it a little bit bigger.
So here we go.
And since you're in role 1, why don't you kick us off?
Sounds good.
Here we go.
There he is, running across the screen.
And then back to Brian, running across the screen.
And we did it.
We did it.
So this dog will just be running forever
unless we give it some instructions otherwise.
But you can see that this could be a great foundation
for building a distributed video game.
And so today, we've learned two things.
We've learned how to animate the sprite on your screen
so that it has an illusion of motion.
And we've also learned how to customize messages
so that we can send a custom message
type with different types of data payload
when we're trying to do something that's
more sophisticated than just saying, hello, world.
We'll stop it there.
But thank you for joining us.
And we look forward to seeing you in our next video.