Hi, welcome back to Programming for a Network World.
Today, we're going to be exploring
turtle graphics in NetsBlox.
Turtle graphics provides a way to express
your creativity by drawing on
a coordinate plane on the stage in NetsBlox.
The ideas behind turtle graphics go back a long way to
the 1960s when a professor named Seymour Papert
invented a philosophy called constructionism that
challenged kids to learn by expressing
their creativity through drawing
simple graphics using computer programs.
We're going to be doing the same thing today and we'll explore
how turtle graphics allow
us to express our creativity within NetsBlox.
Ready to bring out your inner artist? Let's get started.
Here's what we're going to do today.
We're going to draw just three simple shapes.
First, a triangle, and then a square, and then a circle.
But we're going to do it with some
increasingly sophisticated techniques.
But to begin with, let's just talk about what a turtle is.
If you look on the stage right now,
you'll see that Ada is here,
and Ada is actually behind the scenes, a turtle.
Now, you can have one or more turtles on your stage.
But in this case, we're just going to start with
the very simplest turtle representation.
If I go to costumes,
you'll see here that I get this option
to change back to this turtle shape,
this arrowhead-like shape.
I'm going to press that and we'll say goodbye to Ada.
You see here now that we have this turtle on our screen.
Now, the other thing to understand about turtles
is that they have two fundamental properties.
They're located in a particular space on a coordinate plane,
in this case, 0, 0,
right at the center of this Cartesian plane.
They also have a directionality.
In this case, it's pointing 90 degrees.
We have to be aware of both of
those properties when we're drawing figures.
Let's start by just drawing a triangle.
How would we do that?
Well, if we're drawing a triangle
and we're going to make 120 degrees for each of the angles,
we could do it this way.
We'll take 10 steps.
Let's change that to 50 just to make it a little bit bigger.
And then we're going to turn
and we're going to say 120 degrees.
And then let's move this over here
and we'll do the same thing again,
50 and we'll turn 120 degrees.
Then we'll do the same thing one more time,
50 and we're going to turn 120 degrees.
So that should make a nice triangle.
Let's try it out.
Nothing happened.
So why did nothing happen?
There's still one more important concept you need
in order to draw with turtle graphics.
And that is the idea of a pen.
So you see here that there's this pen tab
and you can bring over this two blocks,
pen down and pen up.
As they sound, the pen down will put a pen to the canvas,
so to speak, and allow you to draw with your movements.
And when you pull the pen up, the turtle will still move,
but it won't leave any trace behind.
So let's try that now.
We're going to put pen down and pen up
and we'll try the same thing.
And now you see that we have a nice triangle.
Now, one other thing is if we draw triangles like this,
we'll probably want to come back to the same spot.
In this case, we returned to the same spot,
but I think it's a good practice to get into
to always come back explicitly to the same part
of the coordinate plane and then point
in the same direction.
So here we're pointing 90 degrees
and we want to go to zero, zero, the center of our plane.
All right, and let's try that again.
And there we go.
You'll see that if we point in different directions,
here we can point, for example, to 270,
we'll draw a different triangle.
So we'll come back to the same place,
but we're pointing in a different direction.
Now, what do you notice about this stack of blocks?
One thing that you'll see is that there's
a lot of repetition here.
So there must be another way that we can make this easier
to draw shapes rather than just doing move, turn,
move, turn over and over again.
And we can do that using a control block called repeat.
And you see down here that there's this repeat block
and it allows us to specify how many times
we want to repeat something.
So if you want to draw a square,
we would draw lengths of 50, turn 90 degrees
and draw another length of 50 and so on and so forth
four times.
But rather than repeating this like we did for the triangle,
why don't we, let's just go over here
and duplicate some of this.
So we'll bring this over, we'll duplicate that
and put it on top here.
And then we'll also, well, we can just
pull this out ourselves.
Don't have to be too lazy about it.
So I'll go back over to motion and we're going to move
and we're going to turn.
So we'll move 50 and now we turn because it's a square, 90.
But how many times to repeat?
Four times.
So let's do that here.
And then we still need that pin up and pin down.
So let's do that.
We'll say pin down right before we start moving
and we'll say pin up right after we start moving.
And let's see if this is, in fact, a square.
It is.
And again, we can change our direction.
Here we're still pointing in 270.
We could change it back to 90.
You can actually just type this in too.
You don't have to click on it.
And there we go.
So now we've drawn a square and a triangle.
So let's try for something a little more difficult, namely
a circle.
Now, we're not going to get a perfect circle,
but we're going to do an approximation of a circle,
a polygon that has enough edges that it looks very smooth.
So how do we do that?
Well, we need to review a little bit of math.
We're going to start off by specifying the radius.
And let's say it's going to be 50.
So I'll make a variable for that.
Let's make a variable to capture that information.
We'll just call it radius.
Here we go.
And I'm going to set that radius to 50.
So I'll drop down here and put 50.
There we go, 50.
Now, how do we get the circumference?
Well, there's a formula for that.
2 times pi times the radius, 2 pi r.
And so we can calculate the circumference
using that formula.
So let's make a variable called circumference.
Circumference, if I spell that correctly.
There we go.
And drop that down.
And now we're going to get a math block
to be able to do that calculation.
And you see this little arrow?
We can pop that out so that we have three slots.
Now, the first slot that we need is going to be the 2.
And then we're going to need pi.
So we'll just make an approximation of this, 3.1459.
And then we're going to put in our radius, which we
have up here in our variable.
So that should get us a circumference.
And let's do the calculations here.
So we have a radius of 50 and a circumference of approximately
315, if you want to round it.
And now we need to get the segment length.
So the segments are going to be the number of the lines
that we draw in this polygon.
So let's create a variable, and we'll call it segments.
There we go.
And let's assign that over here.
Now, how are we going to set the segments?
Well, the segments, we're going to experiment
with what makes this polygon smooth enough
that it approximates a circle.
And so one way we'll do that, it was just
take the number of the circumference
and divide it by, say, 10, and then see what that looks like.
All right, so here we go.
We're going to take the circumference.
I can grab that from variables over here, drop it in,
divide it by 10.
And now, one thing that we want to do
is we want to actually make sure that this
is an integer, that is not a decimal.
Because if you look on this right now,
it's going to be 31.459.
We'd rather just go with a straightforward integer,
so a rounded number.
So there is a function over here.
Let's take a look at it.
It's under Operators, and it's called round.
And I think it's right there.
So we can pull this in, and we pull our calculation
inside of round and drop it back in.
Now, when we click on that, you see
we've got segments of 31 length.
That's great.
We just need a few more things here.
So let's take a look at what else we need.
Our segment length and our segment angle.
Now, the segment length, let's take a look at that.
The length, we've got 31 segments,
but how long should they be?
We'll calculate that by dividing the circumference
by the number of segments.
So let's go over here to set that and back to variables.
And let's make a variable.
And let's call it, let's say, segment length.
Segment length.
And then let's assign that here.
Set that segment length.
And we're going to set it, as I said,
to circumference divided by the number of segments.
So we'll need this operator over here for division.
We'll drop it in, and then we need to go back to our variables.
And we'll set it circumference divided
by the number of segments.
OK.
Very good.
And now we just need one more thing,
which is the segment angle.
So we need to make sure that this actually
turns into a approximate circle.
So let's work on that.
Let's get the segment angle.
And here we go.
So I'm going to go set another variable called segment angle.
And I'm going to set that here.
And we'll set the segment angle to 360
divided by the number of segments.
So we'll take our operator over here again, drop it there.
360 and the number of segments.
So we've got that already.
There.
OK.
That should be everything we need.
Now, we just need to add in the other information
that we had here.
So let's do the same thing.
We're just going to go.
We can just grab it again.
We want to go to 0, 0 like we've done before.
We want to point in direction 90 or whatever else direction.
And now we want to use a repeat block.
So let's go to Control.
And we'll go down to Repeat.
And how many times do we repeat?
Well, that's a good question.
We repeat the number of times that we have segments.
So let's go over here and grab segments.
So you can see that you can use a variable here,
just like we've created.
And you don't have to just type in a number.
OK, so we're going to repeat the number of times
that we have segments.
And what are we going to do for each of those times?
It's the same process as we had before.
So we're going to move.
And we're going to rotate.
Now, the question is, how much do we move
and how much do we rotate?
Well, you can see here with the information that we have,
we want to move the segment length.
And we want to rotate the segment angle.
So I'll go back to our variables.
And we're going to move the segment length.
And we're going to rotate the segment angle.
Here we go.
And the last thing that we need to remember
is to put our pen down and then bring our pen back up again.
So that's over here.
And let's see.
So we'll do it right here at the beginning.
And we'll do it again at the end.
So this should do it.
Ready?
Let's see.
There we go.
We got a circle.
Now, one fun thing that you can do,
and I'll just end with this little flourish,
is you don't have to always say what direction you want.
You can actually click on random here.
And so let's do that for these here.
So we're going to say direction for each of these
is going to be random.
And I'll do that same thing here.
Let's see.
Direction is going to be random.
Here we go.
And we can put on some hat block to make it easier to press.
So let's see.
For example, when some key is pressed.
So I guess to make a triangle, why don't we
associate this with a T?
And we can do the same thing here for our square.
Let's make that an S. And for the circle,
naturally, we will choose a C. Oops.
I brought out the wrong one.
Bring that back.
And this one is the one I want.
OK.
Now we're going to press a C for this.
And it will draw a circle starting at the same spot.
We've always said go back to 0, 0.
But it will appear in a different direction each time.
So let's try this.
So we can press T. And we can press S. And we can press C.
And each time we do that, we're going
to be in a different place.
And you can see you can also click on these.
And so you get some good random shapes.
And if you keep doing this, you'll
get some interesting designs.
All right.
So today, you've learned how to draw with turtle graphics
and also save steps by using these loops
so that you don't have to repeat those combination of blocks
over and over again.
I hope you'll experiment with some of the combinations
you have here.
And I look forward to seeing you in my next video.
Thank you.