Hi everyone, welcome back to Programming for a Networked World.
Today we're going to be talking about errors.
Now, if you've seen these videos, you know that I've made my fair share of errors
as I'm working through programs.
And there's a process called debugging
that helps you to identify the source of those errors
and then to correct them.
So today we're going to be covering some of the debugging tools
that are built into NetBlocks and learning how to use them.
So, ready to squash some bugs?
Let's get started.
Okay.
So, today we'll just make a simple program
and I'm going to purposely put some errors into it.
So here we go.
Let me bring over...
Well, let me talk about what this program will do first.
This program is going to divide a number
and then it's going to give you the quotient and the remainder.
So the quotient is the integer part of the division
and then the remainder is whatever is left over from the integer division.
So to do that, let's bring over a program now.
We'll create a program now.
So I'm going to bring over two blocks that we need.
We'll need the mod operator to get the remainder
and we're going to need over here, let's see, floor here.
Okay, and then we're going to divide.
So let's just get these pieces in place.
So if we get 2 divided by, well, let's say actually better, 3 divided by 2,
this should give us the integer part, which is it goes in one time.
And then if we do that same calculation up here,
3 divided by 2 or 3 mod 2, we should get the remainder.
So it's one remainder of one, which is the right answer.
Okay, so let's build this into a custom block.
So I'm going to make a block here and it's going to be an operator
and we'll say, let's call it divide with quotient and remainder.
And we'll need to put in our parameters here, so x and y, and we'll create that.
Then let's turn those into inputs.
Okay, x is an input and y is an input.
There we go.
Now let's build out here our function.
So there we go.
It's got stuck.
That happens.
Sometimes you can just grab another block like this and then drop it over.
So that's a little bit of a bug ourselves that we have in this box,
but maybe it would be fixed by the time you watch this video.
But if it ever happens, that's how you solve it.
Okay, so 3 mod 2, so we don't need the absolute values that we put in here.
We're going to get rid of those because those be the variables that we use.
Okay.
Now let's imagine that we want to return this as a tuple or a list of two items.
So to do that, we're going to make some variable inside here.
So we're going to go to variables and we're going to create a script variable
and we're just going to call this nums.
So there's nums.
Okay.
And let's also create script variables for the quotient and the remainder.
We could do this a little bit more simply,
but I want to make this all explicit so we can sort of look at the steps we need
for debugging.
Okay.
Now let's grab here.
We'll start doing our math.
So first let's do set the quotient to the floor of,
let's get this out of the way, x and y.
Okay.
And then we're going to set, let's see here,
the remainder to mod of x and y.
And then we're going to, under control, report.
There we go.
We're going to report a list of the quotient and remainder.
So we actually need to add this to the list as part of what we're doing here.
So let's do that.
So let's, for example, set,
and we'll just put in here the nums to, well,
let's just add them to the list.
How about that?
So we'll go down to here.
Let's see.
We'll use for this, just this ad.
Okay.
So we're going to add the quotient and we're going to add the remainder.
And what are we adding it to?
Well, this list that we're going to be using, which is nums.
Okay. So that's the quotient.
We don't need this.
We do need the remainder.
And that is also added to nums.
Then we report nums.
So we report the list that contains first the quotient, remainder.
Okay.
Now there are some bugs,
both bugs that will occur at runtime.
That is if a user enters values that we don't expect,
and also bugs that will show up as soon as we run this at all,
because of the way that we're working with lists.
Let's just see what happens.
So, okay.
So we've got that.
We've got this custom block.
Let's bring it out.
Divide.
Okay.
So let's divide three by two again,
and we get an error.
Okay.
Inside error, expecting list, but getting number.
This is very common.
We've seen this before and we know in fact what it is,
but let's pretend that we're a little unsure about why this is causing an error.
So what would we do?
Well,
you've seen me just kind of go through and edit blocks and kind of figure it
out, thinking through the problem, breaking down step by step,
and then building up piece by piece again until it actually works,
which is a typical way of debugging.
But there are some tools that you can use to make that process easier.
The first one I want to show you is the stepping tool here.
So if you say visible stepping and you can click on that,
you can change the rate of stepping.
We'll look at that a little bit.
I'm just going to put it towards the left side because it'll make it a
little slower.
Then I'm going to open this up here so that we can edit this.
And I want, because I want to see what's inside here while we're stepping.
Now,
what stepping allows you to do is to watch the actual sequence of steps
that take place in a way that helps you to see where the error actually
occurs. So if we can click on this now with stepping,
you'll see that it enters into our custom block and it's running through the
various operations.
And you can see each operation as it's taking place.
And then here it breaks down here. Okay.
And this is exactly where the error is. So it's in this block.
So that actually helped us to narrow down where the error was in a really
nice way. And we can say, okay, why did that occur? Well,
I mean, we know the answer.
It's because we haven't set nums to be a list.
We're trying to add nums to something that is not yet a list,
but what if we didn't know exactly what the problem was?
There's another block that you can use that will help us to identify the
error.
And that is a block that we'll find over here under control.
It's very at very much at the bottom pause all.
And it has this like pause label here. Okay.
So let me just stop this. So we've got the visible stepping on,
but I'm going to actually now drop this right into where that error
occurs. So just basically let's say right here. Okay.
This is sometimes called a break point.
Basically it's not stopping our program. It's just pausing our program.
And because it pauses our program,
it allows us to inspect the value of the variables that are you know,
what their state is at the moment.
And then we can see if there's something wrong with one of the variables
that's causing the problem that we're discovering when we try this
operation. So let's give that a shot.
I'm going to turn stepping off and I'm just going to run this like we had
before. So I'll start the program.
And now you see that it looks like it's let's make sure that's right.
Okay. So you should see that it looks like it's paused here. Okay.
And then we can click this button to run it again and then it hits that
error. But when you run it, let's make sure we run it. Okay.
And you see this, that it's paused. It's paused right here.
And now the nice thing is we can click on this and now we get this kind of
set of variables that we can look at.
So these are the variables that are actually being used at this moment in our
program. And if you click on them,
you can display their values in the window here or on the stage,
and you can see what they are. So here we can see.
Now what's wrong here?
Well, we can see that all of these values are integers here.
They're three, two, one numbers is zero quotient is zero.
So let's get the last one here. I guess I stopped it from running.
So let me run it again. Okay. And then the remainder. Okay.
So these are our watchers.
They're showing us the values of the variables at this stage in the program.
Now, if we unpause it, we hit that error and it can help us see, okay,
we know that the error is in this line.
And if we look to see what we're adding quotient to,
you can see that we're adding quotient supposedly to a list,
but we're actually trying to add it to an integer.
So now let's go ahead and fix this.
Let's go over here and under variables,
under variables, we're going to set at the very beginning of the script,
the remainder or no,
sorry nums to a list.
And so let's grab list over here and we'll make it an empty list.
Okay.
And let's unclick these so that we hide them.
We're going to look at them again when we run this.
When we run this.
Okay.
Now let's run it again.
We're going to hit that break point, which we did.
Now we can look at this and we want to look in particular at nums.
And we see now that nums is actually a list rather than an integer.
And so if we run this through,
we see now that nums has the two values that we expected,
and we didn't run into any errors.
That break point allowed us to look at the state of that variable at that
point in time,
and then determine that we had the wrong type of variable and change it
from being an integer to a list.
And that's all the problem.
Now there are other problems in this particular function that we've written,
but they are problems that manifest differently.
They have to do with particular values that might be run through.
So for example,
we could have a divide by zero error and let's just run this through with
maybe don't need the break point anymore.
Now we get the result of infinity and zero.
I'm going to hide this.
There we go.
So it does work,
but we have the values infinity and zero.
Let me just get rid of the break point because we don't need it right now.
And with infinity and zero,
that's because there is no way in mathematics to divide an undefined
operation, a number by zero.
So it gives us infinity.
Now in this particular case,
the way do we want to handle that is probably to check the value of the Y
when it comes in,
but there's other problems here that are maybe even more subtle.
Someone could pass in a letter,
for example,
maybe they thought they were dealing with a variable that contained a
number.
And if you click that,
you're going to get zero and zero.
So it's still not giving you an error.
So we want to check to make sure that the information that we're passing in
our parameters are actually numbers.
The way we would do that is to go back to the way that we've defined these
inputs and to make sure that we require them to be numbers.
That's the easiest way to avoid that type of error.
So let's make sure that there are numbers going in and let's do it here.
All right.
Now let's test that.
And still giving us an A,
but let's try this again.
Now we'll let us type it in because we've defined it to be a number.
So I can't type A.
I have to type a number,
but we still have the problem with zero.
So how do we test?
How do we work with that?
How do we get rid of that to make sure that we don't have this divide by
zero error?
Well,
let's use an if statement then,
and we'll go over here to if,
and then we're just going to test to see this.
We'll put all these blocks in here and we'll say if,
and then we're going to get the,
the value of this.
So we want to say if Y equals zero,
but of course it's not,
if it's equal to,
if it's not equal to,
so we're going to use this Boolean operator to invert that value.
There we go.
So now if Y is not zero,
then do these things.
Otherwise do nothing in this case.
So let's try this.
Now it didn't report because there's no reporter here.
We could probably put in something to report if it's not the case.
It's not the case.
So let's see here.
Maybe we want to say
divide by zero error.
Make sure Y is a,
is not zero.
How about that?
Okay.
So let's try this again.
Now we've got that error,
but if we change it to a one,
then we get the results.
There's no single way to find and address errors.
You have to think about the inputs that you're receiving and the ways that
you're going to defend against those errors,
or if you get errors,
how you're going to show why those errors occurred.
Okay.
Thanks very much.
We'll cover more topics in next blocks in our next video and see you then.