Hi, everyone.
Welcome back to Programming for a Network World.
Today, we're going to continue our exploration of mapping.
In particular, we're going to explore Google Street
View within Netsblocks.
So as you know, Google Street View
allows you to see images of locations in cities and places
around the world.
So ready to explore the world with Netsblocks?
Let's get started.
So today's project will be we're going to build a city
explorer.
We're going to take a list of cities,
and then we're going to take a random city
and then show it in Netsblocks.
So this could be the beginning of a game
that you would make, like a guess the city game.
So we'll set up the structure for that,
and then if you want to continue with it,
please feel free to do so.
All right, so how do we get started?
First, we're going to go over and explore the RPC tab again.
And we'll bring out our normal call block.
I'm going to drop this down, and you see here
that we have Google Street View.
Now, when I expand that and I look at the dropdown,
I see that we have a number of options.
Get info, get info from address, get view, get view from address
is available, is available from address.
Today, we're going to use the get view from address
and is available from address.
So the goal is we're going to pass in the name of a city,
we're going to pass in a few additional pieces
of information, and then we're going to get an image back
of that city, just some random image,
and then we'll leave it up to the viewer
to see if he or she can guess what that city is.
So now, let's just try to test this out to begin.
So we're going to get view from address,
and you see here that we've now got a bunch of slots to fill.
The first one we'll slot, the first slot
we'll fill, which is Nashville.
And then we'll do our normal thing
of going over to Sensing to get the height of the stage
and the width of the stage.
There we go.
Let's bring that over.
OK.
Now, field of view, heading, and pitch
are specific to the Google Street Images RPC.
And so if you look at this, you can click Help,
and it will give you some more detail
about what those particular parameters mean.
In this case, though, I'm just going
to fill this in with 90, 90, and 0.
And if you want to explore using different parameters,
feel free to do so.
So let's try that out.
We should get an image of Nashville.
There we did.
But as you know, we need to put this on the stage.
So let's go do that.
Under the Looks category, we'll switch to Costume.
I can bring this over if I can.
There we go.
And I'm going to drop that in here, switch the costume,
and then there is a random spot in Nashville.
Now, how do we explore other cities?
Well, we need to have the names of the city
if we want to look them up by name.
So in order to do that, we could develop our own list.
We could just type in a list of names.
Or even better, we could find a list
that someone else has put together.
So there is such a list.
And I've got it right here in this tab.
This is a list from GitHub of, I think, probably hundreds
or maybe even thousands of cities from a mapping service.
And so I'm going to use that.
But how do I bring that into Nest Blocks?
Well, there are a couple of ways.
And this is one of the things we'll be exploring today.
If you find data that is not packaged up as an RPC,
how do you get to it?
Under the Sensing tab here, you'll
see that there is a URL block.
So let's put that in here.
There we go.
So that's the link to the data on GitHub.
And if I click on this, you'll see
that it brings back that data.
And you can see that it's in the JSON format.
But the problem is it's just coming back as a giant string.
So what do we do here if this is the case,
if we just get data like this, but we actually
want to compute with it?
This won't work in Nest Blocks unless we
do some kind of hairy parsing.
So what we want to do, then, is go to a library that's up here.
And we're going to open this library under the Libraries
tab.
And we're going to put HTTP.
And it says Web Services Access HTTPS.
We're going to click on that.
And as you know, when we bring in a library,
it appears under the Custom tab as well as
in the location where the blocks belong by color.
And so here, we see that we've got this nice tool
called Listify.
So what Listify will do is take this list
of data that's in string format and convert it
into the nice list of list formats
that we're used to working with.
So let's try that again.
So I click on that.
And now we get this big list of lists.
So that is excellent.
But now the next thing that we need to do
is to convert this list of lists into something that
is a little bit more easy to use.
So you can see, if you click on one of the list of lists,
you see that it's country.
And then you can see here that the next one
is going to be name.
And then this is going to be latitude and longitude.
So we want to pull out the names right now.
So in order to do that, let's develop a block that
will pull out all the names and just make
a list only of the names.
OK, so let's go over to Variables here.
And remember, if we want to get an item of this list,
like item 2, which is going to be the first item here,
we don't want just the item 2 of the list.
We actually want item 2 of every item in the list.
So in order to do that, we're going
to have to use the Map block.
So let's go down to Map, which should be here.
Let's see here.
Map.
And we're going to map this item 2 over the entire list.
I can get that list.
Actually, sorry, it goes in here.
I'm going to move this over here.
I'm having trouble moving things today, obviously.
There we go.
Now, when we click this, notice that the empty slot is here.
So that's going to put each of these items in turn
into this map.
And we're going to pull out item 2, which should be the name.
So now we've got a list of all the names.
And you can see here just the names, no other detail.
But it's still a list of lists, even though it's
shown in tabular format.
And we'd really like to just get to a simple list of names.
So we can do that by doing another map if we want.
And let's do this here.
We're going to take this and put item here, item 2 of.
There we go.
Put it back into the map.
Let's run this.
And now we just have a list of 126,769 city names.
So that's perfect.
That's what we'll use as a basis of our exploration
of the cities of the world.
So now we just need to start setting up
the environment for this.
We're going to create a couple of variables to do that.
So I'm going to go over here.
And I'm going to make a variable called city.
And I'm also going to make a variable called cities.
Let's do that.
All right.
See if I can still click on this.
OK, there we go, cities.
And I don't need to show cities, per se.
I'm just going to show city.
Now, because this particular map is calling out
to this long list, we only want to call out to it once.
Basically, when the program starts,
we want to just call out and get that list.
So I'm going to go over to here.
And I'm going to say, when green flag is clicked.
And I'm going to set this variable here to this map.
OK, I'm going to drop this down.
I'm going to set cities to this map.
And so now, when the green flag is clicked,
we're going to populate this variable cities
with that list of 126,000 cities.
OK, so that's good.
And then we want to now start finding a random city
in that list to display.
So in our next set of blocks here,
let's do this one when we press the Space key.
So when we press the Space key, we
want to pull out a random city.
So let's get our variables here.
And we're going to set, here we go.
We're going to set city to.
And now, here's the question.
What do we set it to?
Well, we want to set it to a random item in that list.
So let's go over to our variables here.
We're already there.
And let's get to item.
Pull that over.
So item something of city.
So that far, we know.
OK, bring that over.
There we go.
OK, so we're going to do item something of cities.
But it should be a random number in the city list,
not just one or some other number that we pick.
Otherwise, we'll just do everything
in the same order, which wouldn't be any fun.
So to find a random, let's go over to Operators.
And here's a pick random.
Now, this will pick random numbers between 1 and 10.
But we need it to be between 1 and the 126,000.
So actually, to get the full list,
the full length of the list, we can go to Variables here.
And we can get length of.
And let's pull this over.
OK, there we go.
OK, so we've got length of.
And now, we want to put in length of the list of cities.
So now, it's going to pick a random between 1
and the length of the list of cities.
So if we click on this, we're expecting list,
but getting a number.
Oh, I think we need to set it first.
We haven't done that.
So now, it's set.
And let's see if we can pick it up.
There we go.
We should be getting random numbers.
And we are.
OK, so this is working.
And we're going to drop this in here.
So that will get us a random city from our list
and set it to the city variable.
Now, it should be as easy.
But I'll warn you in advance, not quite.
We're going to have to do one more piece of coding
to make this really work well.
So let's just try the naive approach, which
is going to drop city into here instead of Nashville.
And then we'll display it.
So let's see how that works.
OK, so we're immediately hitting a problem,
which says right here, sorry, we don't
have imagery for the city.
Sorry, sorry, there is an image.
So the problem is that there isn't a Google Street
View for every city in the world, sadly.
Not every city has been imaged by Google.
So for that reason, we need to filter our list
and remove the particular locations
in the world for which Google doesn't have images.
But we don't know that in advance.
We have to be able to query Google for that information.
So the way to query Google is to go back to our RPC
over here under Network.
And let's bring out this call block again.
And we're going to drop it back down to the Google Street View.
And then under Google Street View,
we're going to say isAvailableFromAddress.
Here we go, isAvailableFromAddress.
If I can get this to click, there we go.
OK, so isAvailableFromAddress will tell us, for example,
if we put in Nashville, and we'll do the 90, 90, 0,
it should come back as true.
But if we put in a city that doesn't exist, like Atlantis,
click on that, well, there must be an Atlantis
somewhere in the world.
How about Porcupine, if I can spell that correctly?
OK, so a city of Porcupine does not exist.
So it should come back false.
So now we want to test, when we look up this random city,
does it exist?
And then show, and only then show,
that the city, the image of the city from Google Street View.
So in order to do that, we need to start by querying that first.
So I'm going to move this out of the way.
And here's what we need to do.
We need to do a loop, basically.
We're going to loop through until we
find a city for which Google says it has imagery.
Now, if you look under our control structures,
we have several loops that we can choose from.
So we have this repeatUntil block.
The question about this, though, is
we want to repeatUntil we meet a condition,
but we won't know what that condition is until we've
actually executed the block.
So we'd rather check for that Boolean flag
after we've run the code rather than before we've run the code.
Now, there are ways that we could make this repeatUntil block
work for us, but we don't have to, fortunately.
We can actually just go here into libraries again
and pick iteration composition.
I typed L-O-L for loop.
And we'll bring that in.
And you'll see that under the Custom tab here,
we now have a, let's see here.
repeatUntil that tests at the end
of the loop for a condition.
And that's what we'd like to use.
So let me bring that over here and plug it in.
And so what we're going to do then
is we're going to repeat this switch to costume.
Actually, let's set a variable here
so that we don't have to keep going through it again
and again.
Let's set a variable.
Let's do it as a script variable here.
And well, actually, I think we could just use city here.
So let's try this.
We'll just reuse it twice.
So OK, so we're going to set city to this.
And now we're going to ask, is that city available?
So we're going to put this block in here.
I'm going to bring this up here again.
Oh, there we go.
OK, so now we're going to repeat that particular operation
of looking to see if that city is available.
And then as soon as we get that this is true,
we'll pass on to the next block.
Now, the trick is we do need to do that Boolean comparison
here, so let's do that.
So we want to say until the city that we've called.
Here we go.
And let's move this over a little bit more
so you can see it is true.
So let's grab the true, false.
Here we go.
Here's true.
OK, there we go.
OK, so we're going to test to see if this is true.
But now, porcupine, as we've discovered, will never be true.
So we don't really want that.
We want to go back to our variables
and bring in city here.
So once we know that a city is true, then we can move on.
But it will repeat looking for cities randomly
until we know that there is a city at that address.
And then, and only then, will we switch to it.
So let's do that.
OK, so keep the same city variable.
That's why we didn't need to create a new one.
Let's try it.
So OK, we're going to populate our list again.
And then I'll hit a space key.
And I think we were in luck on the first one.
That was fine.
El Bon Pastor.
Delano.
Looks like someone's house in Delano.
OK, another city.
All going well.
Ah, but you notice here now we see some cycling going on.
It's looking for a city.
And finally, I think it found Stanford that it could pick.
And so there were several cities in a row
that it saw but didn't have information about.
So in order to prevent that kind of appearance of cycling,
although it's kind of a cool effect in itself,
we can just hide and show the variable.
So let me bring this over here.
Let's do show variable down here.
And let's do hide variable over here.
Here we go.
And I'm going to drop this down.
And it's the city variable that we want to hide.
And it's the city variable here that we want to show.
OK, now when I hit space key, it's still cycling a little bit.
Let's see why.
OK, so hide city variable.
Let's just try it here.
Should.
Oh, oh, oh, I think I've got it in the wrong spot.
We've reversed it, or I reversed it.
So let's take it and switch it around.
So there we go.
So we want to show the variable here.
Then we want to display the image on the stage.
And here is probably where we want to hide it
when we hit space key.
OK, so let's try that again.
So now it's showing a variable that actually has a city.
There we go.
There's another city.
There's a little bit of like you're
switching from the old variable name to the new variable name.
So we could probably fix that if we
wanted to just print this particular city
name on the screen.
But I think, in effect, we've got it working now.
So again, you could take this further
and make it into an actual game by adding an input block
and saying, can you guess what city this is?
With a list of 126,000 cities, that might be a difficult game.
But there are ways that you could perhaps
make it more interesting or more playable
by suggesting three names at random, one of them
being the true name, and then allow the players
to guess which name it is out of those three.
That would be, I think, a fairer game to play.
All right, but that's it for today.
Thank you very much.
And we'll continue this exploration
of mapping in Nest Blocks in our next video.