Welcome back to Programming for a Network World. Today, we're going to be
building a texting application. We're going to be learning about something
called message passing in Netsblocks, and our goal today is to send a text message
to someone who's not actually inside our own project. Curious about how that's
going to happen? Let's get started.
So, to get started with this kind of project, you actually need two people or
you need to open up a separate web browser and run them side-by-side.
Fortunately today, I've got my colleague Brian Bruhl, who you know from all the
tests that you've had to do along the way, and he's going to be helping me out
in being my partner in this exercise. But don't worry, we'll also include
instructions on the site about how you can do this yourself if you want to try
it out alone. Alright, so messages. When you send messages in Netsblocks, you can
send them not only to sprites, but you can also send them across computer
boundaries. So the idea is very similar to what you might experience with email.
When you're writing email, it would be pretty limited if you could only email
other people on your own computer. You want to be able to email anyone around
the world. And so, to do that, you need to send a message to them with a
particular address. Now, the question I remember was when I started with email,
how do I know that person's address? Well, first of all, we need to think about, okay,
where do we find that in Netsblocks? So, in order to find where to pass the
message to, we need to go to this Room tab that you've seen before, but that we
haven't used up till now. And you'll see in there that I have a role. I'm in a
role called My Role, and below it is my username. Now, in order to set up the
environment in which we're going to communicate with these messages, we're
going to need to create additional roles. And I'll create a role, and then I'm
going to invite Brian to go into that role to write his piece of the program.
So this is really a distributed program. I'll be writing part of it, and then
you'll see Brian writing the other part of it, and we'll take it from there. So
to add a role, I can click here, Add a Role, and I'm going to call this Receiver.
And you'll see that it pops up, and there's a new role now in my room, but it
doesn't have anyone in it. It's empty. And My Role, just to make it clear, I can
click on the center here, and I can rename it. So let's give it a name called
Sender. So that's pretty clear. So we have Sender and Receiver. So this is just
going to be one-way texting. We won't try to make the scenario that we might
want to lead up to later, where Brian can actually text me back. I'm just going to
text him, and hopefully he'll get my messages. Okay, so now what I can do is I
can click on this. There we go. And I can say Invite User. And when I do that, I'll
see all the people that are on Netsbox at the moment. So I can see that I'm
there, but I need to look for Brian, and I need to find his username here
somewhere. And it looks like there it is, Brian. And so I'm going to invite him
into the role. And you'll see there that Brian now will be able to accept that
invitation, and in a moment his name will appear. And there it is, Brian. Okay,
fantastic. Now, the thing is, with these roles, they're like whole Netsbox
environments to themselves. So I want to make sure that when I'm programming, I'm
in the right role for what I'm trying to accomplish. So you need to make sure that
your name is under the role that you're using. So in this case, then, I can proceed
to make the script. Now, what kind of block do we need to be able to send
messages back and forth? Well, the main thing is, we need to use, under the
Network tab, this new block called Send Message. And let's just take this Send
Message out here. And you can see that it has a drop-down, and so it just is going
to send a message. And the difference is, between this type of
message block and the broadcast block that you've seen before, is that this
message block has space for you to put some kind of message payload. That is to
say, you can type something in, just like,
hello world, something like that. Or you can put a list, or you can put any
other type of Netsbox blocks inside there, and that will be the payload.
That's what's going to be sent with that message. The other thing is, we can target
this now to the particular role that we want it to be sent to. So I can
send it to Receiver, I can send it to others in the room, or I can send it to
everyone in the room. In this case, I know that I want to send it to the Receiver,
because that's where Brian will be waiting for this message. So I can just
say, okay, send to Receiver. Now, as far as it goes, that's actually all we need. So
once I click on this, there, the message was sent. It's very anticlimactic from
our end, because I sent a text message, essentially, and we're going to have to
switch to Brian for you to see what that message looks like. Hey guys, it's Brian
here. Now that Cliff has shown us how we can send messages, we're going to check
out how we can receive messages. So first, we can, while we're in the Receiver role,
we can see that there are, of course, none of the scripts that Cliff has
written. Now, this is because, as he mentioned earlier, we can think of these
as independent projects. They don't share any code, or the stage, or sprites, or
anything like that. Now let's get started writing the script to handle the
message Cliff is about to send. If we check under the Network category, we can
see right above the Send Message block, we have this When I Receive message
block. And if we select the drop-down, we can see a familiar message type called
Message, which should look a lot like the message type that Cliff showed
you just a minute ago. And now the question, I guess, is what would we like
to do when we actually receive a message? Well, for now, let's just have our sprite
say the message, so we can see what has been sent. Alright, and now we can
see that the message has, in fact, been received, and we see our Hello World
message as soon as Cliff sends it. So now that you've seen what it looks like on
Brian's end, let's make this a little bit more complicated. We want to build, like,
an actual texting app. So how would we do that? Well, let's start building out
the app part of it. So I guess we can go to Control, and we'll bring over
green flag clicked, and let's ask a question that, you know, because you
typically text people some message, something of importance. There was that
app called Yo, and the only thing you could text was the word Yo, but I don't
think a lot of people text that way. People tend to, like, actually text
something of significance. So let's make it possible for people to do that. And so
we're going to go under Sensing and ask, What's your name? And that will allow
Brian to know who's texting him. So I'm going to then take a variable, and I'm
going to set it to, let's see, under Variables here, let's make a variable
called Name, and I'm going to set that variable, we don't need to show it though,
to whatever the answer of this is, and get that under Sensing. So if we go over
here, get the answer, pull it over there, there we go. Now, what else do we need
here? We need to just now fall into a loop that's our texting loop. So let's do
that, and let's go over and get a forever block, bring that over here, okay? And
we'll just continue to ask questions and then send text. So I'm going to drop this
in here, because we'll edit that in a minute, but we need that send message
block. The other thing we need is another block that says, Ask, and this is, What is
your message? And wait. And then the answer to that, we're going to drop in
here, so that's actually what's being communicated. Now, if we want to make
this a little bit more of a kind of distinctive message, because you see
here that we're sending only the answer, but we've forgotten to include my name,
we need to actually change this message type. So the other thing that you can do,
and that you'll find yourself doing a lot, is not just sending this generic
message, but sending very particular types of messages. And you might ask, okay,
well, how do I define the type of my message? And conveniently, there is a
button here that says, Make a message type. When you click on that, you get this
sort of starter message that you can customize. And so I'm going to call this
Chat, and then it asks you for fields. And just like any other block, you can expand
or contract that by hitting those arrows at the end. And so I'm going to
send two pieces of information here. So my message payload now will include two
different types of information. The first is going to be my name, and the
second is going to be, let's call it the message. Now the important thing about
this is, when you create that message type, and I'm going to drop down, you'll
see it appears as Chat, and my answer pops out. The important thing is that the
person that you're communicating with in that other role knows what that type of
message is, because it needs to correspond exactly. If you don't actually
have the same name for your message type, or the same number of slots, for example,
you're not going to be able to send messages that the other person can
receive. So this is something that you need to agree on in advance. And once you
have that agreement, then you can continue to reuse that type over and
over again. So here, I'm going to take the answer, and this, let's just be clear
about what answer I'm using. So I'm going to take over my name, which is available
here, and drop it in the name slot. And then for what is your message, let's get
that one from Sensing, and bring over the answer here. So I'm going to put that in
there. And again, I'm going to be sending it to the receiver. We have the other
options that we saw before, but we'll stay with the receiver. So that should be
the complete program. So let's try it now. It'll say, what is your name? Oh, you
know, we should be inviting Ada to ask us what's our name. So that's a missed
opportunity, but we'll add that in the future version of this. So in any case,
the turtle is asking us, what is our name? And I'm going to say, Cliff. And now it's
going to move into that loop. And it'll say, what is your message? And here I can
say, hello, Brian. And I'll say, how are you today? Again, a little anticlimactic
on our end, because we're not seeing the messages coming through. But we'll switch
over to Brian now, and see what it looks like on his end again. Now that we've
seen how Cliff has extended his sender role to be able to be more feature-rich,
including asking for a bunch of messages in a loop, as well as including the
sender's name, we need to update our receiver role accordingly. And so most
importantly, we need to update the message type to this new chat message
type that Cliff created, just so that both the sender and receiver are speaking
the same language, so to say. So just like, again, we saw a minute ago, we will
click on this make a message type button in the network category, and create the
same message type that we saw Cliff make. So we're going to be creating a message
type called chat, where the first field is name, and the second field is message.
Once we've created this message type, we can see that it has now become available
under the drop-down for the when I receive block. So we can select this chat
message type, and now we can see that the two fields that this chat message
contains are actually available. So in other words, anytime we receive a chat
message, if we want to know the name that was sent, it is available with this kind
of name variable block, and the message field is available using this
message variable block. So now that we have two kind of bits of information
that we would like to say, or like to kind of preserve, we can't just, of
course, fit both of them in the say block anymore. So we're going to need to go
into the operators category, and find some way to kind of join both chunks of
text. Thankfully, there's a block for that. So we can use this join block that we
see here. And just to keep it simple, let's maybe just say the name, put a
colon and a space, and then the message block in next. Now you'll notice that I
accidentally clicked on it and got this little error message. This is just
because the name and message variable blocks are really only available when we
have this, when we received a chat message, because we don't have, of course,
variables for these defined in this project. So if it happens to you, just
don't worry about it for now. Once we drag this within the say block, now when
we receive a chat message, we can see that we'll have access to the name field
and the message field, and it will say the contents of the name field with a
colon and a space, and then the contents of the message field. And as we'd
expect, we can see the message that Cliff sent a minute ago, and we can see
that Cliff is saying, hello, comma, Brian, exclamation point. And now we see the
second message as well, Cliff asking how I am today. And unfortunately, right now
we can't send messages back, so we'll just have to maybe let them know next
time we see them. Okay, today, just to review, you learned about message passing in
Nest Blocks. We learned how to use a room and to set up roles, and then we learned
how to use messages to communicate between those roles. We also learned how
to use message types to set up complex messages that we can then use to send
lots of interesting bits of information that we couldn't fit into single fields.
So with all that now, we can build larger distributed projects that we'll be
working toward in later parts of this class. Thank you for joining me, and I
look forward to seeing you next time.