Hi everyone. Welcome back to Programming for a Network World. Today we're going to
be talking about a way to make it easier to work with lists. So sometimes you get
really long lists of lists and they become difficult to manage. You're saying
index 1 of this list and index 2 of that list, trying to get down to the
information that you want to retrieve. In this video we're going to be talking
about ways to find information in lists by their keys. That should make it a lot
easier to keep track of the items in your list. Ready to find information with
the right key? All right, let's get started.
So let's begin by opening the particular library that we need to use, which is
called the Structured Data Library. So if I go over here to Libraries and it's
down here and I click on that, see I've got a list of libraries that I can
import. So we'll type Structured Data and I'm going to open that and it imports
those blocks. And if you look under the custom blocks you'll see that they're
right here in this list that I can use. Okay, so it gives us several blocks. I
pull them over. We've got a value, set value, delete, and we won't worry about
the error block for now. Okay, so the difference between these blocks and
your index 1 of blocks or index n of blocks is that they will be able to find
information by a key. So it's typical that you might have information that
comes in the form of key value pairs. And it will look like this. Let's just make a
simple list together. So I'll make two slots here and then I'm going to put
inside of the slot another set of lists here like this and open those up. There
we go. Okay, and so when you have a structure like this, the first item will
be your key. So we might say like course. And then the second item will be your
value. So we might say like programming. And then in the second list we could do
something equivalent. So the first will be, let's say, date and the second will
be 2022. Now when we look at that, we've got a nice list of lists. If you
normally wanted to get information from this, you would go to get the item 1 or
item n of block and then you could drop this in here. And you could say, okay, let
me get item 1, which is going to give you course and programming. And then you
might want to say, oh, but I just want to get the value of that. So then you have
to get another one of these blocks and get 2 here for the value. And this
should give you programming. Okay, so that's fine and it works well when you
have a kind of simple list of lists. But the thing is that it's easy to lose
track of where that information is. Should it be indexing to item 2, indexing
to item 1. It's easy to forget what that number should be and then you'll get the
wrong piece of information out. So that's what the structured data library
aims to solve. If you've got lists in this format, then you can use the
structured data library to retrieve the particular values of those key value
pairs by name. So for example, let's assign, we'll make a variable here and
we're going to call this course information. So we can imagine it's like
a course management system that we're doing. So let's go to the variables tab
and we'll set a variable here. I'm going to set this course information to this
particular list. We'll get rid of the item 1 of and item 2 of. Okay, bring that
up here. So we've got the list of lists and I'm setting it to the variable
course information. Okay, so now that we've got this variable, let's bring that
down, course information, and we'll drop it into this slot here. And let's say
that I want to see the course that I'm taking. Well, I can just type in course
for the key. I've got to set it first. Rookie mistake, didn't set the value of
the variable to the list. So you can see that we've got course information there.
So let's try to get the value out. So in this case, I've got the value course and
if I click on it again, I get programming. Okay, so that's the way that it's
intended to work once you set the value. Now, if I want to get the date out, I can
do the same thing. Just type in date. I think you can see that that's a much
easier way to approach these types of key value pairs inside of a list. And you
can also use the same library to set information. So for example, I can set the
value of the course. It's actually not programming. It's programming for a
network world. So programming for a networked world. And if I click on that,
you'll see that now when I go down and bring out the value of course
information, let's say a course in course information, it's now programming for a
networked world. So I can set the value that way and if I wanted to, I could also
delete that key. And now if I go down here, it should return an error because
it couldn't find any key with that or any value under that key. Okay, so that's
the way the library works. Let me show you an example from the real world about
how you might use it. So let's go and get some data from the Internet. We'll go to
our network tab and let's pull over our block here. We're going to call one of
our RPCs and I'm going to get this course information out of the way there.
Okay, I'm going to call one of the RPCs. I'm going to go to the history. We'll go
to the New York Public Library. Let's search and let's search for the term
Vanderbilt. Let's see what we get. We'll get 10 results per page and we'll just do one
page of results. So when you click on this, you get this kind of typical list
of lists and it's, at least in this view, it's got so much embedded information
that it's hard to read. You can't actually read it without clicking into
it. Now we could still take that approach of going to get the item one of and
we'll take a look at that, sort of see what information came back, and we see
that for item one we have four key value pairs, the UUID and the item ID, but we
also have a title and a date digitized. I think what might be most interesting is
for us to just look at the titles of the information that came back. So let's do
that. Now again, like we could iterate through all this with, you know, the item
blocks, but let's not do it that way. Let's use our new library. And so let's
go down to the for each block and pull that over. And the for each block will
loop through this list and each time assign that item to one of the items in
the list. So that's a helpful helper block to have. We'll just drop our RPC
there. So now that we're going to be iterating through each item in the list,
then we can do something with what's inside. And so here we're going to take
this value of and we'll have Ada say it. So I'll bring over the looks. Let's see
here, say hello, and we'll replace hello with the value. Now the value should be
title of the item and she'll say it for two seconds. Now if this works as we
expect, the RPC will go out and get that data, 10 items in the New York Public
Library about Vanderbilt, and then it will go through each one and pull out
the title. And we don't need to remember where the title fell in that list of key
value pairs. We can just say we want the title from each of those items. And here
we go. So now you're seeing that's two items have the same title, but there's a
different title. Knox 1909, number 665, the Breakers, New York City, Cornelius
Vanderbilt, the Commodore, and maybe one without a title, the Vanderbilt Hotel. And
we're at the end of our list. So you can see there that in terms of readable code,
that's a lot easier to read and understand what's going on, not only for
yourself, but for someone else that might want to use your program in the future.
All right, that was our short introduction to the structured data
block. Thank you for joining me, and I look forward to seeing you in our next
video.