Hi everyone. Welcome back to our series on programming for a networked world.
Today's topic is variable scope. What is scope?
We use the term scope in ordinary language to talk about what is relevant to an undertaking
and what falls outside of its ambit.
Perhaps you've been in a conversation about a project and someone says,
that's out of scope. In other words, that idea does not fall within the parameters
of what we've agreed to work on together.
Scope in programming languages is a similar concept.
When you create a variable, you should think about which parts of your program
need to have access to that information and which do not.
By defining the scope of your variable, you keep information restricted to its relevant context.
In general, it's better to limit the scope of your variables
so that different parts of your program avoid tripping over one another.
Ready to bind values to variables? Let's get going.
Let's start with the easiest case, creating a global variable.
This is a variable that every block and every sprite, including the stage, has access to.
So how do we do that? We'll click on this make a variable block,
and we're going to type the name of the variable, namely greeting.
And we'll sign it for all sprites. So I'll say OK.
And there we go, we've got greeting here.
And you notice here that it appears in our variable palette.
And there's a checkbox next to it. And if you click the checkbox,
it will disappear from the stage.
If it's checked, it will show the variable name and its current value.
Now, how do we set the variable so that we could have Ada say hello to us?
We bring over this set block. And here we drop down,
and we can see that we have this global variable in the drop-down list called greeting.
And we assign it a value.
So we'll put hello, world right here, like that.
And we'll click it, and it'll be set.
And you can see now that on the screen right here,
hello world is set as the value of greeting.
Now, if we want Ada to say hello to us,
we'll go up to looks, and we'll click on say hello for two seconds.
But instead of just saying hello, she'll say our greeting.
Now we need to grab that variable, and we'll bring it down over here,
put it inside the slot, and click on it.
And there you go. Ada's saying hello, world.
What is happening here? I created a global variable
by selecting the for all sprites button.
As the dialog box implies, this means that every sprite will have access
to the information bound to this variable.
After giving it a name, I see that the greeting appears
near the top of the variable's palette.
What is the value of the variable when it's first created?
If you look closely, you saw that it was zero.
In NIST blocks, all variables begin life with a value zero.
If you want to change that assignment, then you need to use a set to block,
like we did to bind the variable to a new value.
In this case, I set the value to hello, world.
And now the variable is available to me anywhere in the project.
Actually, it's available across all sprites in the stage,
but not on peer-to-peer networks.
We'll talk about how to communicate information across networks
in an upcoming video.
Notice the gray and orange block at the upper right of the stage.
That's called a variable watcher.
It's used to keep track of the values bound to variables.
Watchers prove useful, especially when you're seeking to debug variables.
That is to understand why your variable does not have the value
that you expect it should have.
But sometimes those watchers just take up space in the stage,
and if you have too many variable watchers,
the stage can be cluttered with orange boxes.
To toggle them on and off, just click the checkbox
besides the name of the respective variable
near the top of the variable palette.
And voila, it's gone.
Since this is a global variable,
all my other sprites and code blocks have access to it.
So if I want to create another sprite,
that sprite can also use the variable to greet us.
So let's do that with Alonzo.
So I need to create another sprite.
I'm going to do that by clicking here, and there's the sprite.
It comes in as an arrow or the turtle.
And now if I want to give it a costume, I can do that.
So let's say up here we're going to give it a costume.
It takes a moment to open the costumes.
There's Alonzo.
Bring it in.
Close.
Let's bring Alonzo a little bit further up.
Now we want Alonzo to say hello to us too.
So I'm now coding within the Alonzo sprite.
So here I'll just bring over the looks,
and I'm going to save for two seconds,
and I can go back and grab that same variable here, greeting,
put it in there.
Now, since I'm inside of Alonzo, when I click on this,
you'll see that it'll be Alonzo that says our greeting.
There you go. Hello, world.
I didn't have to redefine it, though,
because it's a global variable.
It's available to all the sprites.
Notice that I did not need to set the value of the greeting again.
I could just use it in the scripting area of the Alonzo sprite.
However, if I create a variable for the sprite only,
then only Alonzo can use it.
If I set the value of goodbye, for example, to farewell,
you'll see that its watcher prefaces the name of the variable,
and a pin appears in front of the name of the block on the variable palette.
Let's give that a try.
So I'll go now create another variable,
and we'll call it goodbye,
but I'm going to make it for this sprite only.
There we go.
And now you see here that sprite2,
and let's give it a better name so we know who it is.
Let's see. Sprite2 should be called Alonzo.
Okay, so now this variable is set only for Alonzo's use.
So here we can set this, and we can then change this goodbye to goodbye.
Let's just call it goodbyeAda.
There we go.
Now it's set to goodbyeAda,
and here we can have Alonzo say that for us.
So actually I'll just use this block right here,
and we'll bring in that variable this time,
and say goodbye.
GoodbyeAda.
Now I'm going to get rid of this from the stage so you can see better,
but if I move back to Ada and I try to use that variable,
you see it's not available to me because it's private now,
or its scope is only the Alonzo sprite.
We can create a sprite variable with the same name for pixelAda,
and it will not step on Alonzo's toes.
So we can have Ada, for example, say goodbye to Alonzo.
Let's do that.
So since there's no goodbye here,
I can just say make a variable for this sprite only,
call it the same thing, goodbye,
but this will be Ada's goodbye.
And now I can set the value of Ada's goodbye to goodbyeAlonzo.
Here we go, we want to say goodbye.
Set it.
Take it off the screen.
We'll say it.
Oop, that's the greeting.
Say goodbye now.
And you see goodbyeAlonzo.
If we switch back to Alonzo, goodbye, Ada.
They don't step on each other's toes.
But wait, we're not ready to say goodbye yet.
There are still a couple other variables we need to cover.
We saw how to keep variables private to sprites,
but did you know that you can also keep variables private
to stacks of blocks as well?
In fact, there are two ways to do this.
The first is to create a script variable.
You can find the script variable block on the variable palette here.
You can see it right here, script variables.
If you drag this block over,
you can connect it with other blocks in the stack,
and those other blocks will be able to use that variable.
Let's try this out with a simple mathematics example.
I'm going to make a stack of blocks that prompts the user for two numbers,
assigns those numbers to script variables,
and then uses those script variables for calculating the answer.
All right, so let's create two script variables.
You can click this arrow to make two at once,
and I'm just going to call this num1, okay,
and then num2.
And here we'll set...
You notice if I drop down here, I've got them, num1,
and we're going to set num2.
Let's set this one to 5, and let's set this one to 7,
and then we can report...
those two variables.
We need an operator here to add them together.
Here we go.
Grab this one, num1.
Grab this one, num2.
And you should expect that this will report 12,
and indeed it does.
After the stack of blocks has finished executing,
the two script variables go out of scope.
Those variables are no longer available in our program
unless we click on this stack of blocks again.
If we do so, they are reinitialized with values of 0
as if they had never previously existed.
Let's talk about the last type of variable,
namely block variables.
Block variables are essentially similar to script variables.
You create block variables when making custom blocks,
and as their name suggests, they remain in scope
only for the scope of your custom block.
Block variables are subtly hidden
within the user interface of Nets Blocks,
so let me show you how to find them.
We'll create a counter using a custom block.
To do this, we'll create a custom block called incrementSum,
and let's just go ahead and start doing that now.
So I'll right-click here and make a block.
I'm going to have it be an operator and a reporter
called incrementSum.
Say OK. There it is.
If you right-click here, you'll see block variables pop up,
and then there's a drop-down arrow.
If you squint, you might miss it.
You click on that, and you'll see block variables appear,
and then, like before, you can click on that
and give a name to your variable.
If you need more, you can use those arrows to do that.
So here's what I'll do.
I'm going to bring a control block down.
Oh, under variables, I'll use a set block here.
Put it there.
I'm going to set sum to the value of sum plus 1.
And then I'm going to report.
Here we are.
I'm going to report the value of sum.
OK.
The first time you click on the increment block, it reports 1.
Why?
Well, the default value of the variable is 0,
so the block reports 0 plus 1, which is 1.
But now let's click on the block again, and we get 2.
If we click again, the answer is 3.
If we click it again, the answer is 4.
So what's going on here?
The answer is that block variables, unlike script variables,
retain their value after the custom blocks finish executing.
If you use a script variable, by contrast,
it gets reset to 0 the next time the stack of blocks runs.
So a block variable remembers its value,
and you can use it to store information for later computations.
This can come in handy if you want to keep track of the name,
for example, of a player or of the high score in a game.
OK.
So that's it for today.
We've learned about four different types of variables in NetsBlox,
global variables, sprite variables, script variables, and block variables.
Which should you use for your project?
Well, circumstances vary.
In general, you should create variables with as limited a scope as possible.
New programmers like to work primarily with global variables
because they're so easy to use,
but you'll find that most experienced programmers tend to eschew them
in favor of sprite, script, or block variables.
What matters at this point is that you understand the concept of variables,
how to create them and to bind them to values,
and also know how to tell when they're in or out of scope.
Thanks, everyone.
I look forward to seeing you again in our next video.